welcome to the huberman Lab podcast
where we discuss science and
science-based tools for everyday
[Music]
life I'm Andrew huberman and I'm a
professor of neurobiology and
Opthalmology at Stanford School of
Medicine my guest today is David goggin
David goggin is a retired Navy SEAL who
served in Iraq and Afghanistan he's also
a highly accomplished ultramarathon
runner for those of you that don't know
ultramarathons are distances longer than
26 mil and in David's case often longer
than 200 miles for his achievements in
athletics he has been inducted into the
International Sports Hall of Fame he
also held a Guinness world record for
the most pull-ups completed in 24 hours
I should mention that Not only was David
a decorated Navy SEAL but he also
graduated from Army Ranger school David
is also a highly successful writer
having authored two books the first
entitled can't hurt me and the second
entitled never finished both of which
are best sellers David's books cover
many topics including his
autobiographical description of what can
only be described as an incredibly
challenging child and young adulthood
his home was abusive his school
environment was abusive he essentially
had no positive resources directed his
way and in his 20s he found himself to
be obese that is more than 300 PBS
working a job he despised for minimal
pay and it was at that point that David
began an inner dialog OG that forced him
to explore the demons born out of his
childhood but also the position that he
found himself in as a young man and then
began the journey to navigate that
dialogue and transform himself into the
Navy SEAL the ultramarathon runner the
bestselling author and the
extraordinarily positive and influential
man that he is today as some of you may
know David has done various public
lectures he's a familiar face online
because there are so many clips of him
on YouTube and he has done podcast
before however I'm certain that you'll
find today's discussion to be very
different than previous podcasts that
David has been featured on the reason is
that of course we get into his
accomplishments we talk about the
mindset that allowed him to achieve
those things but today David really lets
us under the hood he lets us into the
form of inner dialogue that he has to
embrace indeed that he has to Grapple
with on a daily basis sometimes multiple
times throughout the day and night in
order to impose the sort of
self-discipline that he is so well known
for we also get into some of the
scientific mechanisms underlying
willpower and we talk about David's
current Endeavors that include for
instance his own exploration of science
and medicine for which he has become an
intense scholar and practitioner I
should mention that multiple times
throughout today's discussion you will
hear curse words now David and I both
acknowledge that cursing isn't for
everybody and that cursing itself is
different than than cursing at somebody
nonetheless we do realize that many
people parents perhaps especially might
not want to hear cursing if you don't
want to hear cursing well then this
podcast episode is probably not for you
however if you are comfortable with
cursing or if you can tolerate it I
assure you today's discussion is highly
worthwhile before we begin I'd like to
emphasize that this podcast is separate
from my teaching and research roles at
Stanford it is however part of my design
an effort to bring zero cost to Consumer
information about science and science
related tools to the general public in
keeping with that theme I'd like to
thank the sponsors of today's podcast
our first sponsor is Maui neui venison
Maui Nei venison is the most
nutrient-dense and delicious red meat
available I've spoken before on this
podcast and there's General consensus
that most people should strive to
consume approximately 1 gram of protein
per pound of body weight now when one
strives to do that it's important to
maximize the quality of that protein
intake to the calorie ratio because you
don't want to consume an excess of
calories when trying to get that one
gram of protein per pound of body weight
Maui Nei venison has an extremely high
quality protein to calorie ratio so it
makes getting that one gram of protein
per pound of body weight extremely easy
it's also delicious personally I like
the ground venison I also like the
venison steaks and then for convenience
when I'm on the road I like the jerky
the jerky is a very high protein to
calorie ratio so it has as much as 10
grams of protein per jerky stick and it
has something like only like 55 calories
so again making it very easy to get
enough protein without consuming excess
calories if you would like to try mauii
venison you can go to mauii venison
docomo to get 20% off your first order
again that's Maui venison tocom huberman
to get 20% off today's episode is also
brought To Us by Aeropress arero press
is similar to a French press for making
coffee but is in fact a much better way
to make coffee I first learned about
Aeropress well over 10 years ago and
I've been using one ever since Aeropress
was developed by Allan Adler who was an
engineer at Stanford and I knew of Allen
because he had also built the so-called
aobi frisbee which I believe at one time
perhaps still now held the Guinness Book
of World Records for furthest thrown
object and I used to see Allan believe
it or not at parks around paloalto
testing out different aobi frisbee so he
was sort of famous in our community for
developing the different Feats of
engineering that turned into commercial
products now I love coffee I'm somebody
that drinks coffee nearly every day
usually about 90 to 120 minutes after I
wake up in the morning although not
always sometimes if I'm going to
exercise I'll drink coffee first thing
in the morning but I love love love
coffee and what I've personally found is
that by using the arero Press I can make
the best possible tasting cup of coffee
I don't know what exactly it is in the
Aero press that allows the same beans to
be prepared into a cup of coffee that
tastes that much better as compared to
any other form of Brewing that coffee
even the traditional French press the
Aero press is extremely easy to use and
it's extremely compact in fact I take it
with me whenever I travel and I use it
on the road in hotels even on planes
I'll just ask for some hot water and
I'll Brew my coffee or tea right there
on the plane if you'd like to try
Aeropress you can go to arero press.com
huberman that's a r o p
s.com huberman to get 20% off any
Aeropress coffee maker Aeropress ships
anywhere in the USA Canada and over 60
other countries around the world again
that's Aeropress dcom huberman to get
20% off today's episode is also brought
To Us by eight sleep eight sleep makes
Smart mattress covers with cooling
Heating and sleep tracking capacity I've
spoken many times before in this podcast
about the fact that sleep is the
foundation of mental health physical
health and performance now a key
component of getting a great night's
sleep is that in order to fall and stay
deeply asleep your body temperature
actually has to drop by about 1 to 3°
and in order to wake up feeling
refreshed and energized your body
temperature actually has to increase by
about 1 to 3° one of the best ways to
make sure that those temperature changes
occur at the appropriate times at the
beginning and throughout and at the end
of your night when you wake up is to
control the temperature of your sleeping
environment and that's what eight sleep
allows you to do it allows you to
program the temperature of your mattress
and sleeping environment such that you
fall and stay deeply asleep easily and
wake up up each morning feeling
incredibly refreshed and energized I've
been sleeping on an eight sleep mattress
cover for almost 3 years now and it has
dramatically improved the quality of my
sleep if you'd like to try eight sleep
you can go to 8sleep.com
huberman to get $150 off their pod three
mattress cover eight sleep currently
ships in the USA Canada UK select
countries in the EU and Australia again
that's 8sleep.com
huberman and now for my discussion with
David goggin David goggin welcome man
good to see you again man great to see
you it was late 2016 early 2017 I
believe when you were in my lab at
Stanford yes sir uh we did a little work
later that that day down in San Jose and
gosh uh see you everywhere but it's not
enough so great to have you here thanks
for having me on brother yeah you embody
discipline and doing hard things right I
think you just start right off with the
let's go there the Bold truth but right
before we went hot mics right we were
talking about learning right right now
you're spending some time learning and
doing things that I think most people
probably don't typically associate David
goggin with right why don't you tell us
about that well most people just look at
me as the guy that runs and yells as
he's running and that's uh while I do
that you know to motivate people but
people don't understand that my day is
broken up into segments I work out I eat
I sleep but I spend most of my time
studying so like I'm in the medical
world I'm a you know paramedic in uh in
Canada but I spend a lot of my time
trying to Nuke every single thing about
it because I'm not trying to just be a
paramedic learn about veins and arteries
and how the heart pumps and stuff like
that I'm trying to learn to the point
where I can save someone's life and even
though paramics are doing that all over
the world I'm trying to be that
paramedic that can really dissect
exactly what's going on and figure out
you know what medication goes where just
trying to know just trying to learn you
know the the algorithm of what's going
on man so I spent a lot of time with it
I love the word algorithm because when I
teach biology or try and learn anything
that's related to biology and especially
the human body right I need to know the
nouns yep but it's the verbs that matter
and that's really what you're talking
about like like just saying that that
sits there that brain part there doesn't
tell you how it all works together no so
what does your process for studying look
like like if we dropped a uh
a uh camera in the room but a microphone
into that into your inner dialogue right
gosh wouldn't wouldn't we all love that
but if we dropped a microphone into your
inner dialogue are you waking up looking
at the books and going yeah fresh day
let's learn or is some of the same
resistance that you've talked about
coming up around physical yep work is
that coming up from time to time you
know what I was nervous at first I'm GNA
keep the mother I'm Gonna Keep It Real
I'm G keep it real so I'm not a real
smart guy and what I mean by that is I
was born with ADD ADHD all like my brain
cannot retain information I'm not some
genetic freak when it comes to running
when it comes to lifting weights I'm I
am absolutely the bottom of the barrel
and people will never believe me and
they can just you know whatever believe
what you want to believe so when you ask
me this question about what the studying
look like for
me I have to go over the same page over
and over and over and over again while
Jennifer can look at that page while
she's you know quizzing me she'll learn
it right then as she she don't know
anything about it she will quiz herself
or quiz me and learn it as she's
quizzing me it's the most frustrating
thing in the world how my brain works so
what I so what I do is I literally sit
there with a pen and paper and I have my
books and I go through and have to write
everything down every every single day I
will study the same page until it's
photographic memory from writing the
same thing down and then from there I'll
go back through and relearn again so
I'll learn the bulk of it but then I'll
go through and learn the small things
within that so if it's a medication I'll
learn what the medication does I'll
first I'll learn how to even say the
medication because these medications
aren't like like you know like alall no
it's it's it's very big words so I'll go
through learn how to say the name then
I'll go through learn what the dose is
then I'll go through and this is like
every single day so not like oh I got it
let's just go through no nothing is I
got it every single thing that's so I I
I can't wait to get in this conversation
because everything I do in life it sucks
everything I do in life it sucks that's
why when I was 300 PBS and 24 years old
it wasn't like it had some big
epiphany of let's just go be a Navy SEAL
and let's lose some weight no I knew my
entire life was going to be a struggle
which is why I just ignored it and I
said I'm not even trying to jump off
into this and learn how to read how
to write how to memorize how to become
something I am not but through that
process something happened to me and I
realized that's this is why I feel sorry
for no one in this podcast they're going
to really not like me because people are
going to think that I am maybe lying or
maybe fibbing or exaggerating no I am
literally I was the lowest form on Earth
no Talent no ability to learn and I
literally know what it is to be rock
bottom and to build that up so that
question about learning it's a pain in
my ass and I don't have to do it that's
the thing about it I'm 49 years old and
am a
multi-millionaire I don't have to do
anything so all I thought about when I
was growing up is man I can't wait till
one day get to the point where I no
longer have to do this stuff but what
happens I got older it became a way of
living so how I do every day is how I do
every day it's a it's a discipline it's
a regimen it's a it's a it was a choice
I made
and the choice I made was what are you
willing to sacrifice and what are you
willing to give up to find every bit of
who you are as a human being and I was
willing to give everything to do that so
studying is no joke I love that you're
studying I recall a few years ago I
heard uh some interview or podcast with
you and you just threw out like I don't
know what I'll do next maybe I'll be a
scientist and I and I went yeah I was
like because I knew because I know you a
bit and I see your work out there but
we' met before that if you decided that
you were going to do it right and
learning medicine which is what you're
doing right learning human physiology is
so detailed and people uh out there have
to understand when you look at a
textbook and you see the the veins and
the capillaries different colors in the
when the body's open they're not
different colors right you they're not
so I mean some things are have different
color contrast but it's not like it's
all labeled when you pop it open exactly
and so so the process of writing things
down by hand is important for you do you
so you go back and read those notes do
you think about that stuff on your runs
too or you segmenting your day like when
you're done studying are you heading out
for a run and thinking about other
things or are you still rehearsing the
material in your head so when I write it
down I write it down and I'm able to I'm
actually looking down at this table
right now because I'm back to WR so I'm
actually there right now as I'm speaking
to you I write it down in a way that I'm
memorizing page
69 so I'm writing it down so then
writing it down and that page sync
together in my brain so I'm looking at
the book in my brain right now so like
that's just how it works for me and I
have to do it over and over again so
that page is stuck in my mind so I'm
literally flipping through pages as I'm
taking these tests and I'm taking these
National tests to become a paramedic or
become a advanced EMT or whatever I'm
literally as I'm taking that test I'm
going through and I'm
like and I'm flipping pages in my head
of where that page was and how I do that
is just from how I how I write it and
how it's on the page when I run I can't
recall any of
it I cannot I cannot bring any of that
because I'm running how my mind is wired
now is that everything I do is what I do
because the focus it takes for me to
like right now I'm running
I'm not like a great Runner I'm not like
injury-free so like my first 20 minutes
of the run I'm limping I'm literally
limping because I've had several knee
surgeries and my body was twisted and so
now it's untwisting so people look at me
oh looks like he's limp you know like
limping when he runs I am limping when I
run my body's jacked up so I'm focusing
on how to get the best out of a broken
body so everything I do is a total
focused on what I'm doing at that at
that point in my life so it seems like
you've really trained away or somehow
gotten away from the add that you
mentioned because what you described
it's like a deep trench like a v-shaped
trench I'm imagine like there's a ball
bearing it's like and it can only go
forward in that trench right or back and
it goes forward it's not like sliding
around at the like concave at the bottom
like attention so it's like you trained
that up is there a similar feeling when
you're in the full Focus us of running
versus full focus of studying is it kind
of feel like oh yeah that's the same
Groove but different thing or is it just
completely different world it's a
completely different world complet like
it's just both of them for me is is
suffering but suffering a whole
different way like when I was going
through school I'll never forget I think
I was in third grade and back then you
know ADD ADHD wasn't like you know
here's this medicine or here's this
thing they want to put you in a special
school mhm so for me I was so far behind
in learning that their big thing was
let's just put him in a special school
because he'll never
learn and through that process of like I
don't want to be in a special school I
don't want to be treated any differently
it really like I never took medication
I've never taken medication for this
that's right right now you see me
looking right in your eyes what the hell
is is you know is you been saying right
now and that's that's why I don't feel
bad for people who have ADHD who have
learn disabilities and some are
impossible because you just can't but a
lot of them you can and but people don't
want to go through the process of
focus of teaching yourself how to truly
Focus this is where my message gets lost
it gets lost because I may say you know
MF or F where you know I may be because
that's the passion that comes out of me
because that's it takes every everything
for me to learn a
sentence so when I speak about David
Goggins I can't speak about David goggin
in a way that's just calm and cool
because when I wake up I know the
journey that takes for me to find my
greatness and it's hard every nothing is
easy nothing just like oh I wake up and
I just do this or I do that or it just
know I watch people every day go through
life and it's so easy for me to be where
I'm at today it takes every bit of me so
when I speak about it and as I get going
here you'll start seeing me the temple
will rise the passion will come out
because I'm back there I'm doing what I
do every day to become a human being and
so nothing is easy like running is
running it sucks but you have a choice
to make do you want to sit down and go
back to that guy you once were no so
this is what it takes this it it takes
that misunderstanding of people and
they'll never get it because they were
never David goggin so that is what it
takes for me to do what I do it may take
you something differently so for me
everything has to be in the studying
everything has to be into this
everything has to be in everywhere I am
has to be there me focused where I am
that's why you're my second podcast I've
done since Rogan since the book came out
I don't have time for that because
if I want to be great I'm not trying to
maximize money or maximize people
knowing me I do these things because
maybe someone out there will understand
me and get it and say I can grow from
this guy and others just won't sounds
like friction is something you're very
familiar with I just this a word just is
I feel like it's like cast above us
right now in bold face highlighted
underlined letters is friction is gross
friction like you're you're up in the
morning and I imagine David Goggins
going to the coffee maker stretching out
good morning sunshine and you're telling
me from eyelids open there's friction
yes and that is the thing that people
don't they don't get the biggest
misunderstanding about David gaggin of
all time it's like whether you believe
in God or not I
do he put this lab rat which is me on
this planet and said let me see
what a beat up abused kid who has who
can barely learn barely learn who has a
twisted body messed up messed up
genetics Sickle Cell this and that
let me give him everything that pretty
much disqualifies you from the military
but back then it wasn't as and let's put
him in this and see what comes out of it
so to do that friction you don't wake up
in the morning time and go to coffee
maker matter of fact sometimes you don't
even sleep what it requires is when I'm
at 2 o'clock in the it's 2 o'clock in
the morning and my brain is thinking
about a drug and I got to get up
and look in my book to see if that drug
is how I remember it and this is every
day of my life that's why when I
train a fighter or I train some I'm like
you have no idea how great you
really are because you are using such
minimal minimal of what you have and if
people can learn to
focus this is what's possible while it
may not be pretty like people want to do
a documentary on me I go
no I want you to do documentary on me
because I will have normal everyday
people picking me apart on his life is
miserable who wants to live like that he
looks it's crazy how he it's almost like
he's sick he's
psychotic the most frustrating thing in
the world for me is when normal people
judge a man like myself on what it
really takes to
extract greatness from nothing it takes
every bit of who you are if you choose
that route if you don't Merry Christmas
do what you got to do but yeah all these
things for me like like I told you I'm
gonna keep it real I I'm not coming here
to talk about like you know perform
without purpose because I go through
when I write these books I go through I
try to dumb down David
gas how can I give normal people and I'm
normal but I found something that most
don't want to find how can I speak to
people and give them something from this
crazy psychotic brain that I've
developed how can I give him that so I
sit down with Jennifer for years and
write down perform without purpose
callous your mind armor your mind the
cookie jar the accountability miror
that people can use in their
lives no no I'm glad it helps you but
the barbaric life that I live that you
have to live the almost Obsession that
you must have to be great you can't put
that in the book bro you
can't put in a book you can't you can't
write about it has to be experienced it
has to be experienced and you can't even
after you experience it to write it in
the book it would seem like he needs to
be locked up too too gory it's too gory
it doesn't make sense for a guy that
everything every second of the day he is
trying to extract more from
something he's constantly think he's
constantly constantly disciplined never
going off the path whatever is injured
on him he figures away it's a
conqueror's
mindset and very few people if
any can really understand what that is
like a I'm almost
50 and I've been this way for almost 30
years
like what you do for fun you you never
like like these questions I don't I
don't get them I don't understand them I
don't so yeah I get asked that sometimes
when are you for fun I start listing off
all the stuff like podcasting reading
working out but so some of that
resonates but I think what's
so truly unusual about what you're
describing your
process is that you know from go it's
hard yep and I have to ask was being 300
lb
having ENT I'm using the words you've
described you've said it before you had
a tendency at one point in your life
early on tell lies try and get people's
approval my ass off crazy haircuts
attention seeking and and yet all of
that triggered
something that now is you know is
extraordinary right do you think those
hardships were necessary to flip the
switch
I don't know if they were necessary but
it was something that made me
feel I didn't feel
good it was
easy the brain that I was given as a
child it was easy to go home and think
about what how do I want to be a freak
today how do I want to show up to school
today and be a freak it didn't require
me going home and opening a book up
saying it's going to take me all year to
learn this page so instead of
learning that page
I learned how to become a
character and maybe that character that
I created that 300 pound insecure guy
that used to fake fake it to I make it
type of guy you know let me uh become
your friend let me lie to you until you
like me type of
guy when when you have any kind
of any manhood Womanhood a human being a
soul a spirit any I had no I I must have
just this much pride because that's
exactly what opened the door for me
because every day you were a character
every day you were a clown every day you
open that Spanish book or that science
book or English book and you like you
looked at it was like it looked like a
foreign
language and you're saying where do I
start where do I start and obviously it
was necessary the more I talk about it
it was necessary because what happened
is I became
haunted by the mere fact that this is my
existence and you got to live with that
I live with there for a lot of years and
so I sat back and said okay all right I
know what this takes and when you sit
back as up as I was and I had a
laundry list a table like this of what I
have to do to become just a human being
that can make ends me that can make a
th000 a month just to get there was like
oh my god dude like
how I'm 16 17 I can't read I can't write
and I oh my God I'm so behind the power
curve and my brain is about being
depressed and my dad beat my mom's not
home and kids are calling me at
school and I'm like oh my God man what
the do I
do and it wasn't like someone came
around and said hey man you can do this
this is all me
so people want know where's this cold
man come from I'm not trying to be
cold it's the reality of my life it's
the reality of a lot of people's lives
and so yeah that had to happen for me to
be haunted to be haunted to pull out to
extract the goddamn today that haunting
is something that's still there today
because no matter how much you improve
no matter how much you change who you
are it's not permanent
you don't just wake up and say oh my God
man you're you're David Goggins you
break records you do this you do that
people want to know how are you how are
you able to just be so hard because I
never turned the thing off
because once it turns off I go right
back to the David Goggins that is and
that's the guy that I'm constantly
fighting every day and it's a choice and
that choice makes you misunderstood it
makes you crazy crazy that's why I hate
social media in
2013 people wanted me to write my book I
did it in 2018 took five years and the
reason why I didn't do it I set at the
table and Jennifer was there this before
I I I she started working for me I
started dating her whatever and all
these people were there and they're like
man you got to go on social media and I
was like you man like I'm not
that's it's it's poison it's poison
because I knew what I did to get where I
am and I'm gonna have these people these
normal everyday people fat lazy in
exactly who I
was judging me CU I know it because I
was once them all my hard work all my
dedication I'm have some normal dude get
his little brownie his little dingdong
ho ho twinky sit there with this coffee
picking me apart oh he must be unhappy
he's just do you know
how hard it is to put these shoes on
every damn morning I G have you pick me
apart so yeah there's there's a there's
so much that goes into this that I was
like this I never want anything to
do with it so
anyway I'm not a
psychologist but knowing your story from
what you've written what you've said on
social media and elsewhere podcast and
here now especially right it's amazing
to me and frankly it pulls it my
heartstrings a little bit I realize
that's not what you're trying to do but
that in the course of your childhood and
in your young adulthood that no one ever
got between you and the world no I
forget where I heard it that like if a
kid has just one person that believes in
them right you know and I had my trials
and tribulations but I had great coaches
great mentors I attached to them I found
them if they didn't necessarily find me
right but I'm realizing that your
situation was no one's ever said hey I'm
going to stand here next to you or get
in front of you right put a shield up M
and so it's almost like you've got these
different ver it's all you but there's
versions of yourself that like you knew
social media like I don't know that I
have the wherewithal in 2013 14 15 16 17
right to get in front of myself while
doing all this cuz I've already got so
much going on in here right is that
about right that is right but I had
developed a lot of anger and I still
have it it will never go away for the
normal human beings of this world
because when you put yourself in the
sewer like I was in and please if
someone saved me come out and announce
it to the world there's no one there's
no one so when you know that and then
I'm sitting at a table with all these
smart people are tell me what to do and
and guiding me through my life now
when I'm 40 years old you know I
was I don't know 40 something years old
now I'm 49 and I'm looking at them all
and they're and they're now trying to
guide me on what's right on this
poison and so yeah what you say is right
but for me it was more of I know
now I don't need you to guide my future
I know what's good for me and what's bad
for me and for me it took every bit of
focus I could I know social media that's
why people love to go on there because
they want to show you the good side of
life I'm not teaching good side of life
so I had to figure out a way when I came
on in
2016 of teaching you what life really is
for the majority of us is hell and so
while people love to show you the cars
and the house and the vacations and
all that's good all that's happy I'm
going to show you decide that I know
most you're going through and people
hide very well I don't want to hide
anymore I HD it for 24 years so
that's why now I told you we can talk
about whatever you want because as human
beings the one we the first thing we
have to learn I also stutter real bad
growing up so if you hear me stutter
every now and then is because that was
part of my life also so it's funny human
beings want to show you the best side
and they want to hide the worst side for
me I'm going to teach you how to be
vulnerable because that's the only way
you fix yourself you don't fix yourself
by coming out here and me selling you
some books that's why I don't
have them I forgot them I'm glad people
got something from the
book I want you to learn that the only
way you
grow is how to look at yourself and say
okay like I did table longer than this
what the I have to do to get
somewhere there was nothing good on
there nothing yeah I love playing
basketball I left that out that's
something I love to do I don't care
about that that that didn't make the
list because the list that I had
to live by was it was the very list that
was going to get me at this table with
you to talk to you to the normal human
beings which I once was about how you
can get somewhere and how it looks looks
very ugly
there's no passion there's no
motivation there's no oh my God
man I this is no it's every day
of your life just
doing no passion no discipline no
motivation yeah all these words I hate
people I hate that so many people
use these words now because it's
watered it's someone sitting in the room
by themselves and they figure themselves
out and say God this is going to
suck where's passion when you're 300
lb where's the motivation when you can't
read and write where is it so how did
this happened I just did I just
did I said maybe at the end of this
journey there'll be something there for
me if not I can
read if not I'm 85 pounds there
was not there there there was there's no
magic potion there's no oh let me wake
up and look at some no all those
words are over used they're
it's all just do you're living
how do you want to live how do you want
to die how do you want to be
remembered that's that's it that's it
period as many of you know I've been
taking ag1 daily since 2012 so I'm
delighted that they're sponsoring the
podcast ag1 is a vitamin mineral
probiotic drink that's designed to meet
all of your foundational nutrition needs
now of course I try to get enough
servings vitamins and minerals through
whole food sources that include
vegetables and fruits every day but
often times I simply can't get enough
servings but with ag1 I'm sure to get
enough vitamins and minerals and the
probiotics that I need and it also
contains adaptogens to help buffer
stress simply put I always feel better
when I take ag1 I have more focus and
energy and I sleep better and it also
happens to taste great for all these
reasons whenever I'm asked if you could
take Just One supplement what would it
be I answer ag1 if you'd like to try AG
1 go to drink a1.com huberman to claim a
special offer they'll give you five free
travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 K2 again that's drink a1.com
huberman the word haunted m is ringing
in my head
yep I think it's such a powerful word
yep because I was about to say seems
like a huge part of your process maybe
the entire process is it's all stick no
carrot you know you talk about the
carrot the positive thing and then
there's the stick the thing you're
trying to avoid yep feel like it's the
way it's Landing for me m is it's all
stick and gas pedal that's it there's no
carrot you're not imagining oh when I'm
a paramedic when the book is published
and obviously you set those goals and
you make those targets y but it's all
stick all stick no carrot think about
that I'm waking up right now studying
like I have a test tomorrow I already
passed the
test think about that every day of my
life that's what I must do just to
retain what I
learned four hours plus a day I go
through and do that there's no stick or
there's only a stick there's never been
a carrot which is why when I speak to
people I have to figure out a way to
resonate with them cuz all I want to say
to them
is let me teach you the real life how it
really is the reason why you're a loser
and the reason why you're not
making it and the reason why you're
trying to go through all these I go to
all these conventions speak all
the time I look in the
audience and these people sign up sign
up sign up every year to go to
Convention thinking they're going to
learn something different no
you're lazy you know exactly what to do
exactly what to do because even me in my
state of I can't read and write I knew
exactly what to
do it just sucks doing it it sucks to do
it it sucks to wake up every morning of
your life and say God man I'm I'm not
smart so guess what I gotta do I gotta I
gotta study the same that I got one
of the highest scores in the nation on
and do it again do it again do it again
it's not just there it's not just there
permanently for me so yeah it's all
stick it's all
stick the only care that you have is
like
maybe maybe because whenever I take
these tests that are real hard in the
back of my brain it's like the good
chance you're not gonna make it Goggins
this ain't you
bro this ain't you you weren't born like
this this ain't you the real you bro
study all you want to but the second
that computer comes on with 150
questions this ain't you man and somehow
comes back I passed passed again passed
again but that rued me back here every
time is
saying that ain't you bro that ain't you
and I have to outwork that voice when
I'm taking that test and I get to a
question I don't know the answer
I'm like man and then say I
told you man that ain't you you 300 lb
man you sit at home you figure out how
to do your hair that's what you do how
to come to school with the reverse
baldness when you're
16 that's that that's that's you
so there is no get out of jail free
card this is why I say stay hard because
when you weren't given the gifts the
only thing you can do in life is stay
hard
and I know people cannot stand me they
can't stand this
talk this is all you can do there's no
magic pill or a magic potion all you can
do is outwork the man that God created
or woman in you and what that looks like
is unfun that's why I said do not do a
documentary on me because people will
not see the truth
they will see what they want to see is I
don't want to live like that good good
and you will live exactly the way you
live now questioning who you are
wondering what is possible wondering
what you are capable of doing that's how
that looks or you can be me which am I
happy I don't know never really thought
about it don't really care about it
because all I really cared about was I
looked in that mirror I saw a
piece of happiness wasn't on the
mirror at 16 around 300 lb it was like
oh my I'm looking for happiness no I'm
looking look at myself in the mirror and
say all right you did it
again
today you're a bad boy because that
sucks I have about a couple minutes of
that when I got the
carrot second lay down and go to bed the
carrot is gone because I'm waking up all
through the night to check the work I
did that
day did I get this drug right did I get
this right did I get that
right what did I do oh my God I'm
I'm already losing
it it's a
stick that stick is haunting you
haunting it's following you around so no
picture of Jordan on the wall you're not
listening to YouTube inspiration video
those would be all your voice
anyway uh you're not U listening to your
top 10 favorite songs just to get
rolling and then lace the shoes hit the
books you're it's all in here all in
there I used to do that when I was fat
Rocky I me people know that that was my
thing uh round 14 was my thing and as I
got older and older and older that
started to go away and I started to
create out all these people that I used
to watch Rocky was one Barnes Elias from
Platoon
um Jack from A Few Good Men you know
he's on the stand going crazy I saw a
lot of these characters that I looked at
and I was like man I ain't got none of
that but they were
characters after a
while I lived a life so
disciplined that everybody that I once
looked to these fake
characters I I I built that as a
man and when I was younger I had this
image in my mind of what does a man look
like to me and I got all these people
who are badasses characters
and in my mind I became that and that's
what kept me going a lot was I had this
pipe dream of becoming a little bit of
this and a little bit of that because
when you have no parents raising you and
you have no Role Models growing up you
it's not daydreaming you start to create
a reality
like maybe I can be
that and after
becoming this
guy that is the biggest thing I can ever
do in my life is I became that guy that
I once looked at all these guys now look
at myself like God who the can do
that I can't but what it takes is a a
discipline that no one can ever
even they they just don't they don't
understand it they don't understand
everybody has the ability to do it but
they just don't want to they want to
keep asking questions and keep going to
seminars
and the greatness is right in you that's
why once again I'll say this a million
times here I do not feel sorry for you I
will not sugarcoat what I'm going to say
to you because all of you know what I'm
saying is the
truth everybody knows this the truth
this is what it looks like and you know
it too you know it too this is what if
if you ain't got nothing I hate to tell
you what it looks like is ugly it's not
a documentary it's not an HBO special
you ain't G to watch hey man you guys
gota watch this no it's like oh God this
looks like a train wreck look like a
nightmare this looks like this guy got
no that's what it looks like hard work
looks horrible it's not motivating it's
not motivating at all ain't like Rocky
round 14 he gets knocked down and do
like this to Apollo Creed looks like a
man being stuck in a dungeon and
there's no way out but you have
the
key but you refuse to use it and that's
nothing motivating about that
so yes no document on David
Goggins the real life David Goggins is
the is the documentary it's all it's
already being
written you're it right yeah I'm going
to share a little Neuroscience tidbit
love it but I think it's one that you'll
appreciate um most people don't know
this but there's a brain structure
called the anterior mid singulate cortex
as we pointed out before that's a noun
it's a name it doesn't mean anything we
could call it the the Cookie Monster
right but what's interesting about this
brain area is there now a lot of data m
in humans about some mouse study showing
that when people do something they don't
want to do like add three hours of
exercise per day or per week or when
people who are trying to diet and lose
weight resist eating something right
when people do anything that they and
this is the important part that they
don't want to do it's not about adding
more work it's about adding more work
that you don't want to do yes this brain
area gets bigger yep now here's what's
especially interesting about this brain
area to me and by the way I'm only
learning this recently because it's new
data but there's a lot of it the
anterior mid singulate
cortex is smaller in obese people MH it
gets bigger when they diet MH it's
larger in athletes M it's especially
large or grows larger in people that see
themselves as challenged and overcome
some challenge
right and in people that live a very
long time
mhm this
area keeps its size in many ways
scientists are starting to think of the
anterior mid singulate cortex not just
as one of the seats of willpower right
but perhaps actually the seat of the
will to live see now we're talking and
when I learned about the anterior mid
singulate cortex I was like almost out
of my seat and I've been in the the
Neuroscience game since I was 20 we the
same age and I was so pumped cuz I've
heard of the amydala fear prefrontal
cortex it's planning and action I could
tell you every brain area and every I
teach neuro Anatomy to medical students
but when I started seeing the data on
the anter mid singulate cortex I was
like whoa this is interesting Y and all
the data point to the fact that we can
build this area up yep but that as
quickly as we build it up if we don't
continue to invest in things that are
hard for us that we don't want to do
that's the part that feels so gogin
esque sir to me that we don't want to do
like if you love the ice bath yeah I
love the ice bath and you go from 1
minute to 10 minutes guess what your
anterior mid singulate cortex did not
grow none but if you hate the cold water
if you're afraid of drowning and you get
into water and put your head under
yep then you're anterior mid and survive
then the anterior mid singulate cortex
gets bigger but if you don't do it the
next day or if you do it the next day
and you enjoy it because hey hey I did
it yesterday woohoo happy me marry
Christmas as you say Merry Christmas
guess what the anter mid singulate
cortex shrinks again yep to me this is
one of the most important discoveries
that Neuroscience has ever made MH
because it's that I don't want to do
something but do it anyway that's right
that grows this area and it's almost
like I have a friend he's been sober 30
years from alcohol and he always says
you know the amazing thing about
addiction is there's a cure the problem
is it only works one day at a time yep
and so you have to renew it every day
that's right so the anter mid singulate
cortex to me when I learned about it two
two things went off in my head whoa this
is super interesting and two I got to
tell David Goggins about this and I
waited until now to tell you because I
felt like I well for obvious reasons I
wanted to tell you and I wanted to tell
you here well I love that because that's
how I've lived my entire life I don't
know anything about that
but people go man you have such a strong
will it's something that you build like
I never forgot I was on a podcast one
time and this dude goes you were blessed
with a strong
mind
like the hell you talking about it's
blessed with a strong mind you that's
something that you have to
develop you developed that over years
decades of suffering and going back into
the suffer that's why a lot of people
who graduate Navy SEAL training they
want to know like in my I talk about
very openly all the
time a lot of guys don't go don't want
to go back into that water don't want to
go back into the hard stuff maybe not in
anything hard anything hard in life once
you get through it it's like you become
a
p like how many PS you know want to go
back to p camp none
when something sucks so bad in life this
is on this that we're talking about
now very few people want to go back
they're happy they
graduated I realized I'm the same way I
don't want to go
back I have to go back I must go back
because that is exactly where all the
knowledge of my life exists was back
there and what you're exactly you're
talking about well I didn't know
anything about this but how I grew a
will was constantly doing these things
to now it's just
life I wake up while it still sucks it's
just life you don't sit back and like oh
my God like I have days I don't want to
do but I know I'm going to do
it I know from years of just doing it so
that that that's that's beautiful and
this is why I came on here with you
today and I'm I'm glad you're talking
about this because human beings need to
hear this they need to stop hearing
these
hacks on this and that there's no
hack bro there's no hack
yeah you may this and that and saunas
and all this that they yeah it's
great there is no life hack to
grow that thing how do you grow it do it
and do it and do it and do it that's the
hack the hack is gonna suck and
that's what I realized that's what I
realized life that's why I wanted to
come on here today I didn't want to come
on here and talk about no
passion and purpose and how to get the
out of bed and how to hit a
alarm clock all this catchphrase
because that wasn't how I
lived it wasn't how I lived I lived I
woke up like every human being does and
goes man I'm a piece of
today how the hell is this going to
work out for me and you fight that and
you fight that you don't override it
it's no override button it's the
conversation in your like in
your head so how do you do that we don't
have enough these conversations about
the real conversation that every human
being is having and they have no idea
how to get out of it but they
do it's that right there man you
gotta build your will how do you build
your will exactly what you said man
exactly what you said well I feel like
knowing the name of something interior
mid singulate cortex doesn't
fundamentally change us but one thing I
like about biology is that willpower if
somebody feels they don't have it feels
like this thing that other people have
but everybody unless their brain damaged
like a whole right through their head
has two anterior mid singulate cortex
one on each side of their brain everyone
has One MH they have two so I feel like
it's just a question of opening the
portal and the portal what I again I'm s
to say 10 times and forgive me is I
think people go oh I do hard things I do
sets to failure and then I do four strps
I love training with weights I love
doing sets to failure I even like for
stps but guess what I like four stps so
I I'll tell you they don't build my
anterior mid singulate cortex right
because I like to do it that's right
anything you like to do is not going to
enhance this aspect of Willow and it
seems so obvious once you hear it you
kind of go oh yeah of course but I think
you really close that Loop for people
when you share what you're sharing today
and what you've shared elsewhere before
as well when you're trying to explain
the friction is the critical ingredient
right and I think people think oh if
it's effort well then I'm getting better
that's part of it necessary but not
sufficient as we say in science but the
suck
part The Haunt being haunted the stick
MH they're really unpleasant terms very
these are probably the most unpleasant
terms we've ever used on this podcast
very those are the those are the levers
those are the gears and without those
this thing that you're talking about
David Goggins as a verb right you know I
sometimes make the joke but it's not a
joke right Goggins is a
name and it's a verb people go I'm GNA
goggin that right right but that's I
think again I'm not a psychologist but I
think that's what you're talking about
the stick the friction being haunted
it's the suck part that grows this
anterior mid singulate cortex so now you
know why there's so many people that
fail in this world to figure out their
purpose their purpose in life where do I
go because to grow
that M you may not look like me how my
daily life
looks it don't look
fun don't look
fun so so it's a choice that people have
to make in life but what's so funny
about it is even the richest of Rich who
have everything they always ask me this
question I feel like I'm missing
something I don't feel like I'm missing
I don't have what you all have but
you'll never in my life hear me tell you
I'm missing something everybody is
they're missing this feeling
I found it long time ago I found it
right there in that willpower thing when
you're nothing nothing and change
yourself into something like
me you call it happiness peace whatever
the you want to call
it people are missing exactly what went
on with David gogins why don't you smile
I do I do but I figure something out
that's why I am never you'll never hear
me say I'm missing something I found it
years ago you find it in the
suck you find it in the suck and you
find it repeatedly in the suck to the
point where you know exactly who you are
most people are missing something
because they don't know who they
are they never examine themselves they
they've never done this experiment on
themselves the lab rat we're all Lab
Rats but you're all is the
scientist you create your own self most
people are missing something because
they so much trapped in there I want I
want to say potential I think that's
word used out too much too there's so
much in you that God or wherever the
hell you believe in or if you're atheist
in you that you have not un unlocked
that you walk around with this gorgeous
wife or or great husband all this money
like God I feel like I'm missing
something yeah because it's about 75% of
you is still in there still
chained up because you just didn't want
to find your willpower didn't want to
find your soul your will your heart your
determination your guts your courage and
what that looks like it looks scary like
your little scary lab I went in scary to
wake up every day and say I'm stupid but
I want to figure out a way to be
smarter versus saying man I just can't
do that so you limit this box so so your
box becomes so small of things you can
do my box wasn't even a box it was a
little like little pinhole and
then through examining myself getting
some willpower some courage it became
bigger than this table but that's what
we all do that's why I want to come here
today and talk to you about real
not no like hacks there's no
hacks bro it's you against you you
against you and if you misunderstand
that
you have a real
problem real problem I can understand
you misunderstand me running down the
street shirt off this no yeah I can
I can get it I get it if you
misunderstand what I'm saying right now
today the problem is you and you don't
want to fix
it well the children of wealthy people
are a case study in how not having
enough friction can destroy a life true
statement I mean I could list off
prominent names in the Press but those
are actually the least interesting
what's probably more interesting as an
example is all the ones we don't hear
about because we never hear about them
right they just dwindle and wither or I
think there's this big category of
people I'm realizing as we have this
conversation today that they're not
super successful they're
not struggling MH they're like
successful enough that they never have
to you can get to the point where you
don't have to impose friction and you
even said it right your bank account is
in a place where you don't really need
to do all the things you do probably not
even a small fraction of them do nothing
right but you realize the stick and
being haunted is the uh the fuel in the
engine right and you'd be a you'd be
truly crazy to give that up because you
you've internalized all that right but
most people they're they're good enough
yep for them yep and so they don't
actually want to be better badly enough
in order to
start going rung after rung you well
think about when you build willpower and
think about how much I've
built now that you know about this just
I didn't know about this but think about
how much I've built everything I've ever
done in my life I didn't want to
do everything every day I'm a lazy piece
of
and I'm one of the hardest working
people that ever step foot on this
planet Earth and I'm saying that very
proudly because I know what I do it's
not cocky I'll tell you I'm stupid and I
also tell you the exact opposite of what
I've done it's the
truth it is the truth so imagine how
much I've developed in that time frame
but this the scary
thing why most people don't want to do
that build that willpower is because
this
scary it unlocks a whole bunch of things
about who you are and who you're not and
a lot of people don't want to go down
that journey to discover who they are
and who they're not because it's it's
not a pretty journey I mean I've gone
down it it's not like I went down at
once I go down it all the time and when
you unlock that and you can't just turn
it off like people say hey how come you
haven't retired
yet I built all this
willpower do you think it's G to let me
just retire because my my my knees hurt
it's telling me every morning I wake up
like man I don't my knees hurt mouth my
legs hurt my body hurts but you can
still run so why aren't you
running if you can still run there'll be
a time when you can't lace them up
anymore but you can still
run so I still run when the time comes I
can't run the body will say you just
can't run but if I can still do
something that willpower that I have
created it makes me do it every
day
and that's what they don't get what
builds a human being is you start with
the small building blocks and before you
know it man you become something that
you it doesn't even make sense to most
people because it's just who you are now
that's why I can still run at 50 with
broke with at 4 now with broke down
knees and broke down body because my
body knows you still can therefore I do
second you stop the willpower is gone
and that's beautiful I'm so glad you
brought that to me because I always
wonder what's this separation thing
now at 24 years old I started building
something that I didn't even know was
going to be what it is now at 49 and
that's all it was was just
that this structure anterior mid
singulate cortex has inputs and outputs
from a bunch of places but you'll
probably not be surprised to learn that
it's strongly activated when we move our
body when we don't want to move our
body I feel like it it's like the David
GOG structure right it is and it also
has strong connections to the dopamine
reward pathway and everyone goes yay
dopamine reward everyone loves dopamine
I'm partially responsible for people
knowing a bit more about dopamine but
dopamine's badly understood everyone
thinks dopamine dopamine hits It's about
reward it's about motivation and drive
and there are pain inputs to the
dopamine centers of the brain no one
talks about that everyone's like oh you
want the chocolate you know chocolate
sex all yeah that's all true right
release dopamine pain releases dopamine
the an mid singulate cortex can trigger
the release of dopamine in response to
this thing that we're calling
friction and that's a learned thing
that's something that no animal or human
being comes into the world learning we
all are averse to pain and like pleasure
like sugar fat don't like hot surfaces
right but this is a structure that
learns mhm it has has neuroplasticity
the ability to change throughout the
entire lifespan and here's the part that
I think again is is just neuron nerd
speake for what you already know and
have done and exemplify is that it
people say oh it has plasticity you can
change it but guess what it has PL
plasticity in both directions it can
grow but just as easily as it can grow
it's like Silly Putty it can shrink
right so it requires constant upkeep
right and that answer isn't one that
people are going to like nope they're
like give me the energy drink give me
the supplement give me the yes give me
the sauna protocol that's going to
makeig my anter mid singulate cortex
someone out there right now is going
wait if I took transcranial magnetic
stimulation and I stimulate yeah you'd
probably actually they've done that
they've stuck a little wire during
neurosurgery into this structure this is
actually discovered by a colleague of
mine Joe
parvey stimulate and the patients go I
feel like there's a storm coming and
they go oh is it scary and they go no I
want to go through it they come off the
stimulation and people are
like this is the seat of what we're
talking about right exactly and it
learns so the fact that you've kept this
brain structure I'm convinced if we
imaged your brain it be large and it
would be larger in two years a
year but this is the no days off
rationale because it can grow and it can
shrink I know what you're saying right
now I didn't know any of this and I
never and I always talk to people I I
wish I could just put this on paper and
you're saying it in a way that people
can understand I could never put in the
words on what I
built and the power that is within all
of us but you put it so like in in a
scientific way most people like for me
he's just crazy that's why I don't like
talking about it man I know I'm not
crazy I know what I had to do to get
where I had to go people look at as
crazy because they people that just if
you can't imagine yourself doing
something if you can't imagine yourself
doing something the person that's doing
it is
crazy because in your mind the logic
behind it it doesn't compute therefore
you have to give somebody a title and a
title for me is usually he's crazy he's
this he's that no
no for some reason me wanting to beat
somebody so bad in my life
I created that and I've been trying to
figure out years of my life trying to
explain to people but even though you're
explain it
now this is the easy part them
listening to this is the easy
part the part that why there'll
always be the ones of ones is because
putting that
practice putting that into actual work
no man man no no that's where the demons
come in that's where you're like I I I
don't want to be better I don't want to
be better if this what it takes to be
better I don't want to be better so
everybody's that's why there's a lot of
average and it makes me so mad
every day I walk this Earth and I see
average all over the place and
they want to ask me how did you do it I
can't tell you how because you're not
gonna you're not gonna do it not
going to do it you you're going to
continue being out because every day you
wake up like he say it's not like get
the
coffee make the make the
pancakes kiss the girl kiss the kids you
wake up right to work immediate your
mind is in action no one wants to do
that no one and I don't blame them but
don't be mad when you're laying there in
your bed and you're in the
hospital and you're 70 80 90
years old and you're thinking
and I feel like I didn't do
something because you did you didn't do
it you didn't do
you may Liv a great life man but
you're always G to feel empty inside I
don't feel empty so call me what you
want there's not one empty bone in my
body because I have figured out
that really the magic potion at least to
my life and it's very
rewarding I'd like to take a quick break
and thank our sponsor inside tracker
inside tracker is a personalized
nutrition platform that analyzes data
from your blood and DNA to help you
better understand your body and help you
reach your health goals I've long been a
believer in getting regular blood work
done for the simple reason that many of
the factors that impact your immediate
and long-term Health can only be
analyzed from a quality blood test now a
major problem with a lot of blood tests
out there however is that you get
information back about metabolic factors
lipids and hormones and so forth but you
don't know what to do with that
information with inside tracker they
make it very easy because they have a
personalized platform that allows you to
see the levels of all those things
metabolic factors lipids hormones Etc
but it gives you specific directives
that you can follow that relate to
nutrition behavioral modifications
supplements Etc that can help you bring
those numbers into the ranges that are
optimal for you if you'd like to try
insid tracker you can go to insid
tracker.com huberman to get 20% off any
of insid tracker's plans again that's
insid
tracker.com
huberman people like to talk about what
they used to be able to do I hear this a
lot you know you should have seen me in
high school I always laugh yep like yeah
okay got it um and it's not just guys
you should have seen me working out in
high school I was super fit um people
will look back to a time where they felt
like they were capable of something and
now they're not and you kind of want to
just grab them and go wait that was you
then it's you now and but people tend to
think about how the
conditions that were around success
must have been part of it and you can
understand why it's like it's very
rational I was in that situation I was
successful I'm in this situation I'm not
that was the past this is the present
Ergo capable right you see how people
get into these loops and as you
mentioned you spent the first 20 years
of your life in extremely challenged
circumstances and then you can see how
people get to a point where like
everything feels hard like when you're
300 lb I haven't never been 300 lb
but I can't imagine it feels good to get
up and move around he defeating I got a
friend he's in excess of 300 lbs we've
been trying on him for years but no no
win and he's got crazy psoriasis on the
back of his calves and he he actually
smells bad sometimes because he he um
can't wash as well as he would he's big
big right and uh it pulls all my
sympathy right you know but life is very
hard for him and getting worse he's a
young guy with a lot of medical issues
now
for obvious reasons and so I think
people like that think well it's already
hard why would I make it
harder your message is a little
different and you have the life
experience it's a lot different you've
been there so for me saying oh yeah lose
weight you know I was a skinny guy who
got to be a less skinny guy so I don't
really have a foot to stand
on what do you say to those people who
are like listen I'm getting up in the
morning is hard trying to not dissolve
into a puddle of my own tears and my own
misery is
hard you know why people connect with my
book so well for some reason God put me
in almost every up situation on
the planet Earth so when I talk to
people it's not sugarcoated because I
I'm not saying it from I'm I was 175
pounds my whole
life I don't say much to those
people I maybe you're a piece of
maybe you're you want to be nobody maybe
you're happy exactly where you are in
life cuz obviously you are maybe you
don't have the determination to be
somebody better than who you
are and if you want to live with
that I'll support you in that if you're
good with being who you are that every
day you wake up and every day you smell
like because you can't wash your
body well and your Skin's messed up
because your Health's so bad and you
can't put your clothes on right you need
help with that you need help like when I
wasam I need help wiping my
ass that makes you feel
good nothing I can say to you if every
day you wake up with this see people are
haunted but they obviously like horror
films because they keep watching the
same movie I don't like horror
films a lot of people like horror films
so I don't say much to them I say
exactly what I said to you right there
because I was once you I didn't like
horor film so I changed it some people
are just they become like you said it
gets real small when you're lazy and
you're fat your
will their will is so small that they
don't have any and you can't give it to
them there has to be something this is
this is what I'm talking about now
because this isn't a hack this has to be
in you something in you has to wake up
and usually the only person that can
wake up up is you sometimes you can read
a David gaggin book because I was all
this and then a lot more of
up but if you don't have a little flame
you know just that just barely you're
done I can't I can't light it for you
and that's the harsh reality of this
life that I want to get across so
bad you can watch me you can
watch you you can watch Rogan
and Cameron Hayes all these
you can go to Tony
Robinson all this
do all this
if you you could keep going back
and keep spending money and spending
money and spending money with no results
you're gon wonder wow maybe let me go
try out David Goggins he ain't gonna
help
you you have to explore examine the
insides of yourself and what do you
really want out of life your friend a
lot of people out here just don't
want it so guess what
have fun with your life go from 3 to 350
to 400 to 450 to 500 because you don't
want
it and that's the harsh reality I can't
give you you can't give them
we give you ideas but in the day when I
was losing the
weight I had to miserably wake up every
morning in the cold because it was
Indiana November when it started
I was
miserable this is your new
life take it or leave it there's no
happiness about it there's no peace
behind it it sucks it just sucks
and that's the one thing if I could
teach anybody anything it just
sucks and it's going to continue to suck
and then one day you get to a a special
part in your life that it might get a
little bit better but to lose the weight
you have to lose my
friend sorry it's going to suck every
day because then when you're 300
pounds you're gonna go out to lose
weight you could probably get
injured so then you got to work on the
injury and then you get even more
depressed this is what I went through
and then you're hungry because now
you're depressed it's it's just a
vicious cycle and if you're not strong
mentally and you have no willpower
you're going to continue falling back in
this hole versus the man that sits back
and goes all right this is
why I cuss CU this is what is in me this
this is what it took for me to be me
sorry it didn't take hey okay we're
gonna do this today no this
really sucks this is real dude this is
real and every day I'm I'm I'm I'm set
back I'm set back I'm set back I'm set
back so this what I would tell your boy
this what exactly what I tell him every
day you wake up you're going to probably
be set back for the first four weeks
before you lose to significant weight
because of the mind is going to be
with you the whole time there's
no
dopamine there's no dopamine in there at
300 pounds you got nothing your hormones
are
shot you have to Envision something that
is more powerful than
you something has to get you out of bed
and you have to create it it has to be
false cuz you're not it you're a fat
piece of and that's the reality of
it so you have to
create a false reality to live in that
just to get to work on
yourself that's the
reality he'll he'll see this and he'll
appreciate that message we'll see what
he does so far last 13 years it's been
no movement but I've had other friends
who uh who were drug and alcohol addicts
who quit after one conversation never
went back that's awesome that means the
they won it yeah just one one guy I
won't out him but walked up to me at a
party in 2019 July 4th party and said uh
I'm a pile and I go what and he goes I'm
a pile look at me I'm 60 pounds
overweight I go do you drink he goes
every day I go how much he goes a case
he goes I smoke a lot of weed but he's
successful in other areas of his life so
I said well here's what I know quit
alcohol and weed for you you know I'm
not telling people what to do don't eat
until 2 p.m. get on the exercise bike
and pedal in the morning like someone's
chasing you with a poison dart till you
want a puke and I was kind of half
joking right and then uh two months
later he was like I haven't had a drink
I lost 30 pounds he lost that 60 lbs he
never went back now he's he's super fit
it's amazing so some people flip the
switch he is very self-critical by
Nature that's what flips he super
self-critical yep that's what flips the
switch
yeah think about it man we know what to
do we don't need Angie huberman to tell
us what to do we know what to do every
one of us that's why he flipped it so
fast because he knew what to do he
didn't go by your exact
protocol he didn't go by the exact no he
knew exactly what to
do and you just saying some to him
it woke something up he knew what to do
and that's the thing that people need to
get that you know what to do why aren't
you doing it and I'm talking about
myself now you know those modes of just
kind of passive consumption they're so
easy to wash over us I used to have this
thing and I'm fighting this now because
I knew we were going to have this
conversation today where I like to start
things on the hour or the half hour
right worst practice in the
world for me because if I miss that half
hour I'm like ah it's 12:30 3 I'll start
at 12:45 right ah it's
12:45 I'll start at 1 I just lost time
right and then and so this is so stupid
right and the other day I was like man I
got to tell David about this because my
new thing is I start no matter what time
it is right if I wake up in the middle
of the night I got a friend he Paints in
the middle of the night I'm like you're
an insomniac he's like I don't know I
just do it then sometimes he goes back
to sleep sometimes he doesn't everyone's
got their thing but I thought about this
I'm like I'm no more am I going to say
I'm starting it one cuz I I know me if I
miss the 1:00 Ding and my Pen's not
hitting the paper not typing in the on
the keyboard I'm not going to do it
right like that that's a self- admitted
weakness I love it man um I had that for
a lot of years um I know I'm going to do
it that's the haunting part is that it's
going to happen it has to happen and
that's a fact like there's no get out
your free car bro none like that is a
life that I don't know I don't I don't
have
that ability or I have the ability I
don't have the
um I'm not good enough smart
enough I'm not talented
enough to do
that some people are some people can
start at one some people know have to
start it off if you lack Talent you
can't sit back back and
say I start in half an
hour I can't do that I got to start now
and after I get back from starting I
gotta start again and when I get done
with that run or that study session if
it wasn't good enough I gotta go back
again because repetition is what is is
is what taught me everything so you can
honestly outwork anything but it's that
you obviously are a very talented man
well I I have worked hard at certain
things and built up some things that
I've been good at most of my life you're
amazing Gathering Tru organizing and
disseminating information something I've
been doing since I was a little kid I
used to give lectures at school on
Monday about stuff I learned over the
weekend see check that out but they they
took me to a psychiatrist we're the same
age back then if you got sent to a
psychiatrist me people thought you were
crazy one exactly was exactly so so I
remember feeling like a freak I also I
didn't have a stutter but I had a
grunting tick it comes back when I'm
tired D and the only thing that helped
that was hitting my head on something
shaking my head which is why
skateboarding was good because I'd slam
and I'd feel like feel good that's not
healthy you know that's not good or just
work work is what gets it out it's like
an it's like a RPM or high you know
anyway that's me the but yeah I think
certain things over time I feel like
talenter gifts or whatever you want to
call them but there are many things that
are exceedingly difficult for me and I
and have learned from your example I
know that you you are very both humble
and very clear that like you don't have
you say I don't you're not going to get
it by examining you but I think the way
you're sharing today and the way you
shared on other podcasts before there
are pieces that really help people feel
into the process of what you're talking
about today we're elaborating on it I
think a lot you know this notion being
haunted and the stick right I mean of
course of course now it makes so much
sense why you don't want to talk about
sleep or rest or recovery cuz that's
sure that's important I've heard you say
yes you sleep yes you eat yes you
hydrate yes you you will stretch your
soaz or what but it's funny how that
becomes the viral message that's why I
said that today but that's not the
unique that's not the the unique message
that you carry like anyone can talk
about that so do I have that right that
you're acknowledging sleep is important
recovery is important but that's not
what you're about you have to forgo
something
yes ice baths saunas sleep nutrition all
this so important dude I
don't have time for some of it to get to
extract where I had to extract something
had to give like you talk about you when
you were younger you would you would
give these speeches and stuff the same
age you were giving speeches I was
trying to figure out how to saythe
without
stuttering and I realized as I got older
that all these things are
important but for me to stop stuttering
I got build
confidence and speech therapy didn't
help that nothing helped that I have to
forgo a lot of to be as up
as I am to build confidence for me to
stand in the room of 10,000 of
one person and not and be like oh put my
head down let me look around let me let
me um read these paragraphs first and
then before I read the paragraphs cuz
they call me next let me just leave the
room kind with
stutter that's a miserable life and
that's one of many things I did besides
lying besides being insecure besides
being immature besides being fat besides
being one of the only black kids in my
school there a lot of things I had to
overcome to gain
confidence and in doing so a lot of that
had to go a lot of it so I became the
guy that became once again misunderstood
you only sleep four hours a day two
hours a day sometimes you don't sleep at
all like what's this and what's this and
what's this I know it's all
important I can't something's got to go
for me to get confidence because
confidence is the building block of
where I'm trying to go for me to gain
confidence in myself this up kid
has got to do a lot of up to
gain confidence and along the way the
stutter went away and I gained
confidence and now my life is a little
bit
more there there's no
balance there's no balance it's a little
bit more what it should be for a lot of
people but there'll never be balance
because confidence is something that you
constantly confidence and
belief You're Building every day and so
something's got to give and I'm willing
to forgo a lot of things to have that
because I know that is that is if you
want to give somebody
Kryptonite take that away from so
yeah I I don't sleep sometimes and
sometimes I don't eat the right way and
sometimes I don't do this and do that
and whatever man but you put me in a
room with 10,000 people any time of the
day and I walk in there think I'm the
bad in here because I know
what it took to be on this stage and a
lot of people will not do that so that's
what it
takes there's a question I've been
wanting to ask you since we started and
I thought about coming in here and I've
been thinking about in the weeks ahead
of this and I'm gonna just come clean
and say I don't exactly know how to ask
the question just ask it so it's about
relationships oh do it man
so I know in myself MH that my
discipline is much higher when it's just
me but that's because I had certain
things early on but then I had I was a
terrible student barely finished high
school but then when I got serious I got
serious but I did that by staying away
from
everybody and anyone's who's ever had a
relationship of any kind but in
particular romantic relationships knows
that yes you can derive tremendous
support from those like you got this
baby you can go and you're like yeah I
got this she said I got this you know
feels great to finish something and
share with someone share a meal you know
get the hug it but there's another side
to all of that right that I'd like to
learn more about from you which is
there's a warm body next to you in bed
in the morning you don't want to get up
they also have needs you've got your
mission
there people sometimes need things from
us but also often times the people that
love us most that truly love us and that
want to support us don't understand this
thing MH and they're the first people to
tell us like
listen take a day off and then this
whole cycle at least in my head goes off
like you just want a vacation and then
it's almost like a paranoia I'm not
saying anything nice about myself right
now right oh good man former
girlfriend's going to be like yeah like
like you know that they remember they
and and so support of people close to
you is critical MH this could be friends
could be romantic Partners whatever but
they're also the the knife Cuts both
ways it can be the thing that can really
undermine this thing that you're talking
about because the people that care about
us also want to see us comfortable right
they want to see us happy they want to
see us peaceful they want to see us in a
wake up from a great night's sleep and
they want things too right so how do you
untangle that whole bit well it's funny
man I'm I'm going balanced but I'm
mostly unbalanced towards the family
side people don't get about me I start
being unbalanced I get all my stuff in
but what I do is I make sure that my
family has everything they
need everything they need those who want
to be part of my family some don't some
family members don't want to be part of
David ckins I get it I got it that's
life those who are part of my
family I give them everything they need
so they can leave me the alone
I make sure you're happy as because
I gotta go to work and I don't mean
smoke jumping I don't mean running I
mean all of it it takes every I can't
have you in my can't so I
know for me to have a family I gota make
sure that you realize I'm gonna give you
everything you need so when you start
bitching at me I'm G say look hang
on I dedicated my life to give you
everything you need I need this time
right here for for me to be the best I
can be because this journey started
without anybody and I make sure
everybody knows that who comes in my
life I've been left think about it I was
left alone at a long at a young age to
figure the
out I figured it out for myself and it
been very successful for myself no one's
going to come in here and with my
that's why I make sure I will take
care of whatever you need whatever you
need from me you got it money house my
love my support I'm going to give you
everything you need that said I do it
the highest level possible I'm saying
with Jennifer in the Next Room so please
come here and say something if it's
wrong Jennifer I don't give a say
what you got to say so then when it's
time for me to go to work I expect you
to do the same for me because it takes
every bit of me to do what I have to do
so I make sure that I'm very unbalanced
for my family so I can be exactly that
unbalance for myself and that's how I do
it I let people know right up front I'm
not what you
want in a man I guarantee that there's
gonna be a lot of late nights a lot of
early mornings a lot of times where I
gota be by myself thinking about the
process that is next in my mind I can't
have aggravation I can't have this can't
have that there's a lot of things but I
let them know up
front I'm very vocal about that
sometimes relationships work for me
sometimes they didn't but that's who I
am one thing I did wrong in my life was
I tried for so many years to please
people and I did it at the expense of
myself I was leaving a lot in the tank
and I and when you do that you stop
living but the person in your life is
happy as cuz you're giving them
everything they want they have their
their life is full but you feel empty
and that's not a relationship to me so
for me it's important that you know
exactly who I am because this is what
life made and I'm not trying to change
it because I just figured it out so I'm
not trying to compromise David Goggins I
will
never ever compromise David Goggins that
doesn't mean I won't give you what you
need and what you want and what you
desire but I don't need money I don't
need Fame I don't need so I give it
all
away what I do need is to make sure that
that
willpower is worked on every day
and every night for the rest of my life
because that's the one thing that's G
keep me feeding you keeping you where
you need to be because once that
willpower is gone 300 pound David
Goggins he may not be look like it but I
will walk around with it so the things
that are important to you in life you
must do always or you're nobody and
that's how handle
relationships Amen to that something I
could personally work on is that upfront
clear communication because I I it
resonates that feeling of like there's
something inside that's not getting
worked out that I was when I'm on my own
it's it's it's it's a lot easier but
then of course wanting relationships and
family I think that's a healthy part of
Being Human Too obviously you've worked
it out so I appreciate you sharing that
I don't think I've ever heard you talk
no people are scared of that man people
are scared of that conversation with
their wife husband girlfriend boyfriend
and but why are you scared of
it why are you scared to tell a
your wife your husband who
you
are who you are exactly who you are and
that was the problem I had that's a
problem that a lot of us have in life no
one knows who you really
are no one knew who I really was I went
to a school where there a lot of black
kids a lot of black kids didn't want to
be in Special Ops I never talked about
special ops with black
kids why I was wondering what I'm not
going to fit
in that's not what they do a lot of
black kids don't do that kind of so
whatever I wanted to do no one really
knew the real me growing up because I
never want anybody to know the real me I
was always afraid of what you might say
or how you're going to feel or whatever
you got feelings
you have a life that you have to live so
it's important that whatever is on your
mind you let that person know therefore
you're giving them the option to be with
you or not this is who I am if you don't
like it that's good man I I got it but
this is David gogins so there that that
honest conversation is very important
man so everybody knows where they stand
that person may not be for you that's
all good this world could use a lot more
of that upfront completely honest
conversation I feel like so much of the
world's problems are because everyone's
dancing around the issues a lot recently
in the news seeing people losing their
job because they won't say something
publicly you can tell they kind of want
to it's like people just I think deep
down really crave the direct message
like what are you about what are you not
about but I think now everyone's afraid
of getting cancelled it's a big deal
right you know getting canceled that
people think oh I can't work if I am who
I am or or um if I'm not pretending to
be somebody else than you know silence
is considered you know agreement you
know there's all sorts of complicated
stuff and I I do feel for the generation
coming up because we didn't have social
media right and all of that that getting
just walled off from that there's a real
benefit from just not paying attention
people love to lie people love to lie
you know I thought I was the only person
grow like like when I was growing up I
thought I was only person that lied
because I live in the bubble and people
love to lie about who they're not they
love to lie about who they're not dude
and that's for me the reason why I'm so
vulnerable and I'm so real and
honest find somebody to come out tell me
I'm lying about my life and for
me to come where I came from and how the
resume I have now you know the
confidence you get how I don't care who
you GNA you g to judge me you're gonna
judge me what have you done in your life
so me being so honest and so upfront and
so truthful that came with me finally
figuring out who I was but also
conquering David Goggins the Demons of
David Goggins therefore now you're just
an open book you look at somebody
looking right in the eye tell me exactly
who the you are you walk away I'm
good bro I know exactly what this
journey took to get here and that gives
you a fire and a passion that people can
call you they can call you if
you're a lesbian or gay or bisex call
what the you want if you put
yourself in the
fire and you come out every day
like this fresh it off not scared to go
back in there again come on man your
truth is real you come out every day man
with a way of talking to people that
people don't have because there's no
truth behind them and the truth is a
starting line when you sit down the ugly
mirror and say I'm this I'm this I'm
this I'm this you finally started your
life maybe 40 years old maybe 40 years
old five six kids wife but second you
look in that mirror and you say I'm this
I'm this I'm this I'm this I'm this well
basic I'm not this I'm not this I'm not
this I can't do this I can't do this I'm
all these
insecurities your life finally started
and once you start that life man the
truth comes out big time because you
don't long care so that's the problem
most people just don't want to have that
conversation to the point where they can
go on stage with a million people and
say I'm always this and have a good day
see
you it's it's empowering it's very
empowering I feel like the the way we're
educated in school but also outside of
school is we're trained as human beings
these young brains to try and figure out
how to get positive feedback from other
people yep it's like we're we're like
little dogs y you have a bulldog I had a
bulldog saw the picture of your Bulldog
she's she's great they're Charlie dog
they're an amazing species they are I
think of them uh
economy of effort y or amazing breed
excuse me they're an amazing breed
economy of effort they don't do anything
unless it's necessary it's kind of the
exact opposite of everything we're
talking it's kind of interesting that
and they're kind of heeding this now it
is true that they will they'll die to
protect you oh yeah and it's an instinct
I saw that with Costello I'm sure that I
saw with Charlie yeah it's it's an
instinct but if they're not in that
position if there's no need to exert
effort they're resting yeah so your
Bulldog's resting for you you yes got it
exactly so you don't need to rest cuz
active recovery Charlie perfect that's
it perfect that's going to be your
answer from now on does he sleep does he
rest go no he somehow worked it out so
his Bulldog does it for him
right but we're sort indoctrinated into
this way of being from a time that we're
young where of course praise feels good
right someone tells you hey I like that
shirt or good job today or nicely done
or I for me cuz I like growing up in a
big packet friends growing up and I was
never the greatest athlete wasn't
terrible wasn't great Etc like a fist
bump or like a feeling crewed up and
you're just like yeah but you've talked
about this before in reference to the
SEAL Teams we both know a lot of people
in that community and the teams
component is a big part of it for a lot
of people and it's a wonderful thing
right but there's a danger to
that dopamine hit for lack of a better
way to put it from what we could only
derive when it's coming from outside
you're talking about being able to
either say good job but also like just
look to one's own personal history and
say I I've done hard things and I can do
it again and again because I do it again
and again and again you're talking about
parenting yourself yep inspiring
yourself yep scaring yourself all of
that from the inside so very different
than the way we're raised which is to
figure out how to get the biscuit
it's funny man people want to know how
I'm always
motivated it's the Unseen work which you
just says a true statement those are
false dopamine hits that people are
giving you man there's no belief in that
these are team work dop me like I'm out
running at 2 o'clock in the morning 1
o'clock in the morning in the gym long
sessions by
myself you that's real how I'm I able to
just extract dopamine a good dope for me
whenever I want
man I've trained 99% of my life
alone no one packed me on the back I did
all of the work
alone and while I'm still hard on myself
I know what I did so whenever times get
bad for me people all this who's going
to carry the boats and lot that's real I
hate that people know me for that guy
because that guy is not every
day like when they see me they want that
energy that's not me every day I can
extract it immediately when I need to
because when you train alone and I lived
alone for so many years in this misery
and you're able to get out of it by
yourself I can take myself to such a
level of real real passion and purpose
and like the feeling I get is something
I can't even expl by myself I don't need
anyone that's why that's why people come
to me to motivate them no one can
motivate me I have a resume full of
motivation that whenever I'm
down like oh hang on oh you
know you know the truth you know the
truth you know the darkness of the
Dungeons and the demons
that fly you know and then from there
it's like okay you were there you know
this there was no one there to pick up
the ruck sack to pick up the boat to
pick up the log to go in that it was you
it was you there was no pat on the
back at 300 at at 275 at 250 at
220 no that was you so those things that
come out of me that extract from me in
the darkness people are looking for that
P on the back where is it oh I don't
need it because what I've done is in the
unseen
work I built
Frankenstein so whenever shck gets nasty
David gogins Goes you had nobody anyway
so see I'm talking myself
right now that's
me that fires me the up that
makes me nuts you had
nobody anyway look around
you there was no team it was you
there was no weight loss program or Mom
and Dad waking you up saying you can do
it you can be better trying to build
belief you built belief when you had
nothing Rock Bottom you did that so as
times get hard for me
the truth comes out and my truth is
powerful as it's real it's tangible
I feel it it comes out of my brain as I
speak about it I'm reliving every single
dark moment of my life to be
here so that is what people don't get
that is what motivates David Goggins is
the Unseen work but everybody needs that
P on the back they need that training
partner they they need that
accountability coach I don't need that
and neither do they but it's what
we've trained ourselves to believe that
we need it's almost like there's this
pill on the Shelf I'm speaking in
analogy right and we take it and we get
jazzed up we're like yeah but there's
this other medicine cabinet behind there
and it's in US you're saying the the
real medicine cabinet is inside oh yes
when you continue to
overcome and I had so many obstacles
overcome so it's actually a benefit to
me but the benefit is not like a benefit
like that you have to have the courage
and the patience to overcome and
overcome before you know it man you have
a whole medicine cabinet but there's no
medicine in the there's no
preworkout I don't take none of that
all I gotta do is flip my
brain put my finger in there and say
okay that's a good one it's all I got to
do man I got got the roll ofex of just
like go yourself Goggins and oh but
you won let's do that one today there's
nothing I need and this is the thing
that people don't get about David gokin
I can't teach it in a one minute
video we all have this
ability to have our own medicine cabinet
but unless you go in there and put the
medicine in
there it's always going to be fun empty
man you always going to need the
Pre-Workout you going to need I don't
drink coffee I don't do c I don't do
none of that I don't need I I can run
for 70 hours and I had before no
caffeine I got all this wonderful
that I overcame On My Own by myself in
the darkness that man when it's cold I'm
hot when it's hot like I I I can feed
myself all the time and that's why when
people say man why aren't you missing
anything I can't explain it to you man
can't explain it to you you you you'll
never understand that's why I don't do
all these podcast dude I got I I love
you man that's why you my first book you
did a blur for me that's why I'm here I
love what you're doing for people man
but I can't explain this I can't I can't
explain this because people don't want
to do this they don't want to do this
man but it's I don't know man I get I
get jazzed up even talking about it man
because so many people think my life is
just so oh God his life is horrible like
don't don't follow him he's crazy
really but there a good number of people
I would say and that's an that actually
do I think it I what I'm hearing today
and it's really sinking in is that a
great many people either partially or
completely misunderstand you yes I'll
put myself in the partially category big
because I thought it was about just like
forward Center of mass carrot carrot
carrot carrot but it's the stick it's
the stick and it's being haunted and you
know I do have examples from my own life
which is not what today is about about
being really afraid and then turning
things around right my biggest fear is
getting comfortable right I do not have
as much of a stick oriented approach but
today's conversation changing the way I
think I'm not going to step away from
this and think okay there 25 neural
circuits that can explain 10 of the
things that David's talking about and
what I'm thinking about is the fact that
everybody has a brain they have a
mind forget the brain the brain is just
the physical structure but what that
manifests what that creates is the
mind and everybody has that so I do
believe that everyone has the capacity
to do what you're talking about at some
level I also will be the first to
confess that I think you're are highly
unusual let's just say
maybe even n of one as we say in science
sample size of one right somebody who
has created this process for themselves
and keeps them in this themselves in
this forward centered Mass with the
stick battering the back of their head
all the time right highly
unusual but this internal medicine
cabinet that you're talking about
building up true confidence not needing
anything from the outside I think I like
to think M that people want that they
want to be known they're
afraid but that they want to be known
for who they really are and that you're
describing the path to do this right and
I will say I'm immensely grateful that
you're talking to us this way today
about things that you've talked about
before but we're hidden in a little
differently I like to think very
different
because what you're talking about is a
process it's verbs it's all verbs all
action and it's not about success it's
more actually about keeping that
friction dialed to 10 right and that I
no energy drink no supplement people
often misunderstand me they think you
know like I'm big on people getting
sunlight in the morning so they can set
their circadian rhythm and get better
sleep so they can Etc but then people
always think they go straight to the
supplements yeah what should I take you
know and then of course people think I'm
all about supplements and supplements
are one piece for me but it's like tiny
fraction compared to the the doing the
dos and don'ts that's why I didn't want
to talk about that today that's why I'm
glad we're talking about this this this
is it this is it like the brain is the
most powerful weapon in the
world and it's it's crazy how a kid that
wasn't real smart I was forced to go
only
internal external had to go away the
external world had to go away and living
so deep inside myself it was me in this
brain and figuring out how this thing
works and it's so many people are doing
exactly that the supplements the this
the that and I agree it helps but once
you figure out your your
brain you become
Unstoppable to almost anything yeah you
can't beat Death you can't whatever
whatever your brain is amazing once you
feed it the right conversation the right
mental nutrients the right mental
supplements the right the right internal
dialogue at the right time with the
right hit with the right proof of what
you've done in the past and you send
that right to the right circuit dude
you're a
beast a beast but once
again you just can't read about it you
can't sit back and be a theorist you
have to be a
practitioner and in that practice is
where that becomes proof positive what
I'm saying is like God like David goggin
he's blowing my mind what is this he's
not crazy and so many
people a lot of
people have listened to me the right way
and they come back and they're
like I'm totally on board I it happened
it happened I'm
like it'll keep going man if you keep
doing it but that is it man there's no
sign
there's no glory there's no carrot
there's no
Victory but there is all of it in one I
can't explain it real well to people man
but what you get the other end is
something that you're not you're always
found you're never lost anymore doesn't
mean the Journey's easy doesn't get any
easier but you're always
found I love that I just want to hover
on that for a sec the same way we
hovered on haunted and the stick
I think people feel lost I've certainly
felt lost at times in my life um many
times and yeah there's that thing I
don't think there's a neuroscience or a
psychology term for it someone will say
put it in the comments and say oh yeah
that's what so and so said but like you
said we're not trying to be theoretical
here we're trying to be practical the
business of finding
yourself and knowing
like but it's sort of like I'm safe
because I'm in danger and I've been in
danger before and I got myself out
it Al always seems to come back to verbs
again I don't have a language for this
you know for once I'm lost for words
there's like it's it's about a a process
the algorithm and you're and the reason
here I'm just kind of trying to make
sure I'm understanding things correctly
one of the reasons why it must be
uncomfortable for you to be who you are
publicly is because people want to focus
on the running or the swearing and by
the way the swearing is is welcome I'll
tell you I came up through Laboratories
where all three people I worked
for swore a lot but there was one rule I
couldn't swear at people so my graduate
adviser brilliant woman unfortunately
she died early they all died
early I'm the common denominator I had
that internalized for a long time anyway
she said but if you swear at people
you're out right but you can swear as
much as you want so that's that's the
rule I have it's like you can swear as
much as you want just don't swear at
people if you swear at people better be
ready to fight definitely not going to
fight you so you can swear at me get
away with but the fact of the matter is
that it must be frustrating MH that
people cuz I know people go oh it's it's
all about supplements and Ice baths
listen I like supplements I love
supplements and Ice baths but that's not
the full picture they just a
gravitational pull it's the swearing
it's the running it's his feet that are
all messed up it's the fact that he got
a Triton yeah he this seal guy yeah talk
about that too right you know and
there's a gravitational pull for people
and they're missing like the that's like
the tip of the iceberg is what I'm
realizing I'm realizing that today
thanks to the way you're phrasing things
because the bigger vessel is all in here
and and as you said how do you put that
in a book it it's impossible because
it's highly individual you do it your
way yes and you're saying everyone needs
to go figure out how to do it their way
for them yes and the thing about being
misunderstood is very frustrating more
than I can even imagine I I I can't even
express how frustrating it is when
the cussing and everything comes from a
place of of of real I can't explain what
I do without it the passion comes out of
me it's almost like speaking in tongues
because when you put that much work and
people go oh yeah there's been this
basketball player this football player
this
dude no no
everything everything is work everything
and people don't don't believe it so
when I
speak the and the and the
and and and the and is that is
what it took for me what it takes for me
the anger the passion
the the the the jawdropping just it
takes that because I'm not that this is
how I look at it man
what built this guy let's imagine being
in the coldest water you can possibly
take I always go back to hell week with
this I hated the water hated it you're
sitting there locked arms and you're in
the water all the time and they're
bringing you in and out of the water in
and out of the
water when you have this dialogue in
your head and these people are judging
me off of a freaking one minute
video and you're constantly your whole
life when you figured it out 24 I gotta
I I just gotta this gota and
this is just gonna suck every day is
gonna suck and live like that to be
better and I put this way I'm in the
water the water's going over my head the
Pacific Ocean you know it's
freezing February cold as been
through three hell
weeks for you to constantly win win win
when this voice over here the real you
they saying get the out of here go
you're nobody you've always been nobody
and it's true people don't hear that
that's a true voice that's the real
reality of David
Goggins at 24 years old it's not a false
reality and then you had to create
another voice over
here that is saying you're better than
that other voice and you're in the
freezing cold water that
both voices don't want to be
in but you
win and goes from the water to the
studying to the running to the losing
weight to how you eat to how you
function as a man every day of your life
you're winning these
battles and then I have normal
people who only have one
voice never created the second voice the
winning voice is the second voice they
have one voice
and that's just I'm a piece of
that's all they hear and then they
judge people like me who are out here
trying to be
better it's something that I can never
really it's a frustrating thing for
me because I know I know the majority of
people I know what goes on in brain
because I studied the mind more than
almost more than you because I wasn't
I'm a practitioner so for you to be a
piece of and come out of that you
don't just come out of it you spend
decades studying your mind and the human
mind on how it functions in good
environments bad environments stressful
environments patient environment you
studied all because you have to put all
this together to create the mind to
become successful so I had to it like
God blessed me with this brain I had a
Crea a mind and so in doing so I figured
out every piece of human being in
the world because that's what I was
going off of for
myself so I know why you go on Instagram
I know why you because you just have the
time you have the time because you don't
want to put that time into bettering
oneself so I know why I'm
misunderstood I'm misunderstood by
people who have plenty of time on their
hands to misunderstand me because they
are exactly where I once was which is a
lowlife lazy piece of and it's the
harsh reality of people who troll you
who go after you they have nothing
better to do with your lives it's not
some after school special it's the truth
by once was that way I know where it all
comes from that's why it's frustrating
to me now because I'm not so frustrated
at the fact that I'm being trolled
unforunately about the fact that you
don't have the
courage the courage to try to be
somebody better than which you're not
and that's the frustrating
part it's interesting because earlier we
were talking about relationships and you
said in a very candid way and I really
appreciate you sharing that that you
make sure that the people close to you
your family has everything they need
right and that they also understand that
you're going to take what you need to
continue to build you right period
period in some ways
it seems you've also included the
general public in that family you're
saying
listen I'm going to give you what you
need I'm G to give you as much of myself
as I can except I'm going to stop right
at the line that's right that if I were
to cross it is going to prevent me from
continuing to build myself and by the
way this relationship only exists
because I don't cross that line that's
right and I think as much as there are
detractors out there or people that cry
right I mean it's pretty whatever
they're doing is pretty feeble in my
mind I mean it's like cap gun fire you
know if if that very few you
know so many of us men and women old and
young hear something and feel something
in your
message well like yeah like it seems
kind of crazy gosh like doesn't he ever
just relax you know what about his sleep
you know look at his feet he's going to
he's going to injure himself I've heard
listen I'll be very direct I got friends
who were in the teams who just go yeah
what's he going to do when he can't run
and I know the answer is keep running
that's right right but it's more
comfortable for people MH even high
Achievers especially High Achievers to
believe that if you took one thing away
that it would all go away it's
absolutely clear that's not the case
with you I'm 100% convinced I just know
that because what we're talking about
this do many times I haven't been able
to run two heart surgeries multiple knee
surgeries and after every knee surgery
they say you're not going to run again
and I'm fine with
that there's no running up here bro none
this was what it was all about that's
what theyve lost if you can't run give a
it was never about running why do
you think I run it's the worst thing I I
hate doing it more than
anything hence the willpower right your
an mid singulate cortex would would
start to regress if you loved running
think about it every day I wake up I
don't just run a mile two miles it's the
one thing I hate the most to do and I do
it like I love it 250 60 7 300 mile runs
at one time no sleep and every step when
I get to think about this I get to the
start line cussing at
Jennifer why the am I here I hate
this
after 7 some hours of running every
question I ever had is
answered every question I had is
answered I cap
success I don't people go what do you
mean you cap
success for me to be who I
am so when I go smoke
jump I'm smoke jump three to four months
out of the Year sometimes five could you
just for those that aren't uh educated
about uh just like give us a brief
description of what smoke jumping
entails so basically you you jump into
fires not into them but Jump by fires
that people can't get to so out of
planes and helicopters right out of
planes parachute it's all parachuting so
you parachute out of airplanes and then
you fight the fire you and sometimes
four other guys or maybe eight other
guys guys and gals and you're putting
this fire
out so I lose millions of dollars every
summer to do
this it blows people's minds why the
hell are you doing this and you're
breathing s I'm breathing s knees are
jacked up H hitting the ground hurting
whatever talking to normal people They
never get it so I don't even explain it
to
them but this is why this why I call Cap
success I'm talking financial success
for me to continue having that
willpower the
second I just become a speaking monkey
and Trav around and speaking gigs 12
months out of the year put camps on do
this put on lectures get supplement
lines and do this and write more books
and I've
ruined the exact thing I worked on my
entire
life and while I didn't know it until
today but something always told
me this is a very very very perishable
skill this this willpower that you have
cuz I do have a willpower that I have
never seen in anybody my life is a
haunting force that just keeps me going
and I know that that is my strength if
you have that
so that's worth every dime I've ever
made in my life is the fact that I can
look at man in the eye finally and have
a real conversation without going like
this because I'm lying or I'm a piece of
or I know who you know how a person
in so many people do this they're
talking to
you on who they want to be they're lying
to you and they walk away I've done that
so many times you walk away like God man
why can't just tell them the truth how
the hell can I just tell him the
truth you know how good it feels for me
now to look at you in your eye and every
man and man I see because women won't
get this women will not get this man to
man that man you look in another
man in the eye and you know that
everything you're saying is real
and it comes from a real working Place
something that you earned it's the best
feel in the world you can say that
actually happened like I know with
certainty what I'm saying actually
happened actually happened who I am and
who I say I am I am no more lies no more
skirting the truth no more and
that is worth every dime I've ever made
in my life and I is I swear to God on
that every dime I've ever made in my
life building who I built so I cap
success because I know that if I ever go
12 months out of the year and don't put
several every day I'm going at it but
several months out of the year I go
right back to Ground
Zero which means I'm just David
goggin no Goggins no carry boats
logs it's just pick up that
palasi and
dig hey get that pump walk down
a mile put in the water
mosquitoes beating you're just David
goggin you're nobody because that's
where my growth is that's where my
willpower comes from and that's where it
stays that's why I talk to you now and
then can talk like this dude people
don't talk this kind of passion because
it ain't there it ain't there they're
they're regurgitating some from 30
years ago I'm regurgitating
from an hour ago hour ago come on man
it's just
be real and I can't be on these podcasts
I can't talk to anybody without being
real I'll go away I'll go away because I
I can't give you what I want to give
you you said perishable skill I think
that's another word set of words I want
to highlight because skill implies
behavior and when we were just talking a
second ago about the Deep true Bedrock
sense of confidence that comes from
looking someone in the eye and telling
somebody something that you absolutely
know it's true because it happened
you're talking about actions not talking
about perceptions you're not talking
about what you believe happened you know
it happened and there's something really
concrete about actions I mean that's
what's so interesting is we're talking
about the mind but actions are the
manifestation of the mind and I and the
stuff that just stays in
here people die with that it doesn't go
anywhere I I long ago somebody said you
know I forget what the context was it
was a neuroscientist he said you know
most emotions like they're just emotions
they're just in there like you don't
have to do anything with them and I
think certain emotions you want to do
something with right but I think people
forget this they feel miserable like
they're going to dissolve into puddle of
their own tears no one ever died from an
emotion right but they feel like they
overwhelm us as if it's a tital wave
it's going to pull us under and drown us
it's so interesting to me because I
think what people listen you have a
gravitational pole people can feel the
energy I think yes you're either
completely badly or partially understood
there's only one guy on the planet that
truly understands you I think there's
one woman Jennifer who probably
understands you as much as anyone's
going to and then the rest of us are
kind of grasping trying to figure it out
right but you're saying go inward MH so
first go Inward and then it's actions
Inward and actions now the inward piece
is something I'd like to just spend a
little bit of time on because there
couple characters from history people
that were in concentration camps Nelson
Mandela I mean I'm not sure he had
Instagram in there I'm pretty sure he
didn't right and I don't think there was
anyone coaching him on like hey you're
going to get out someday and actually
you're going to lead an entire country
I'm pretty sure that's not how it worked
he had to find it here he had to find it
between his ears right and there are
other examples but that's an important
one so the process of going inward does
it for you and here I will ask for
suggestions cuz I think people want
there are those of us who want to build
this skill
right wall yourself off phone off yep
for big portions of the day perhaps
MH texting off the requests the this the
that anyone that knows you knows that I
we've communicated a few texts but most
of it comes through a filter she's great
she knows you you know and she knows how
to protect your time and that hurts
people's feelings people get mad about
hey God bless God bless you Jennifer you
know cutting oneself off when you're in
there you say it's just
you and the voices that come up are not
pleasant and then at some point it
converts to
action okay how much what is the process
of picking the action that's the piece
that I feel like we there's like a a
bridge to build here if you can if you
would so the action mean like like like
what's next yeah so what like when you
go go to sleep at night when that
happens you know what you're going to do
the next day it's pre-planned yes okay
yes it's it's always the same thing
you're not building it on the Fly no
nothing's on the Fly nothing so how it
works internally for me is I'm I put it
exactly how it is I'm an
artist and every day I'm put I'm I'm
painting mon
Lisa every day and but it's a different
one it's not the same painting so every
day I wake up you though I do the same
thing it takes a different way to get
there so every day in my mind I'm going
through my mind I'm just
like and a good painter will not just
paint he needs to create and you can't
create with phones and everything going
around you so you gotta block yourself
off you only do two podcast in the year
you block yourself off and you're and
you're painting this thing inside and
you're going through all these different
colors of paint and everything else and
you can only figure out the right
painting if you spend the correct amount
of time in your brain so every single
day I'm literally going with my mind and
I'm painting I'm creating this this
masterpiece and the Masterpiece is
always myself and but to do that you
cannot have any distractions because if
you're talking to an artist and he's
trying to to think about the next
painting he he can't it's impossible to
listen to you and listen to what your
mind and body are telling you we must do
people don't do enough of they don't do
any of it you're they don't have passion
they they lack passion Drive
determination because you haven't spent
time with yourself your mind will tell
you what is
next but you haven't spent the time to
go all right let me just figure this
this
out you're looking for let me Google
this and let me Google that and let me
you're not going to find it there
because there's billions of people in
this
world and they're all supposed to be
individuals but we have a packed
mentality that's why you're so
lost why am I so
unique I'm being exactly what the I
supposed to be I ain't f and when I
did follow I was like everybody
else the second I said okay man hang on
dude you don't like this you don't like
this you don't like this who are you
David goggin who are you supposed to
be miraculously all these things
just I I couldn't even the the list of
I had to do just Wham like
okay wow once you sit down with yourself
and say okay I don't want to be like
Michael Jordan or Jim Brown both put on
my birthday so I I looked at their
birthday like oh my maybe can be one I
can't I'm going to be David
gogin and that looks like this it just
came everything flooded so every single
day of my
life there's a different thing that
comes up that I have to do but no one
knows what to do because everybody else
is following
steps like the Republican and Democratic
parties
I'm not political neither am I at all
for this reason Republicans are going to
vote
Republican Democrats are going to vote
Democrat you're not even a human
being bro no way all you agree
with all the same
and I know I don't so once you
figure out yourself and who you are all
the answers come so every
night a different painting is being
painted and this beautiful painting for
myself I'm like okay that's that's it it
may look the same to most
but the end result is very
different that's why my l i if
you look at what I've done in 49 years
it's more than most people ever do in
their life because they were a race car
driver that's what they did they drove a
car it's
great I was all kind of because
that's exactly what the painting was
saying to do what the mind was saying to
do when saying this driver a cars to
them that race car driver know what the
to do he he re ties from being a
race car driver and they're
lost how how are you still I don't get
it dude you're never going to fill your
list but you never found your list
because it never was presented in front
of you because your head was cluttered
with
because you never just stopped for
lots of
minutes lots of years and just said all
right it's me and
you let it go and it just bam it's right
there it's right there I'm not a
psychologist as I mentioned
before but I'm going to venture a
hypothesis
here I
think that you've mastered the process
of internal dialogue but when I say
dialogue I think most people think oh
the the inner voice the the the chatter
but that's just one half of a dialogue a
dialogue is a two-way
street so I completely agree because I
know from experience that when we go
inward oftentimes we hear things if
we're really honest with ourselves it's
like I I don't want to think about that
or that no and then we start looking
outward or we start trying to shift our
attention and
distract and there are a million reasons
that are handed to us excuses and
seemingly good justifications to be able
to do
that but dialogue is a two-way Street
and it hit me while you were just saying
what you were saying I was paying very
close attention and I
realized David gogin is talking about
the voice that comes up including the
terrible stuff that no one wants to hear
about themselves from themselves but
then he's also got the dialogue down
where he knows the counter voice right
he goes yeah you're right and so I'm
going to do this or
maybe no remember this you're in a
dialogue a two-way dialogue in there not
a one-way chatter dialogue there are
books written by famous psychologists
about chatter trying to shift your
internal narrative you're like bring the
internal the internal narrative that's
what going inward is about but it's not
one voice again there's a hypothesis I'm
not claiming to be all knowing Lord
knows I'm not all knowing okay but
you've mastered the dialogue and if
there three
voices strong medium and weak in there
you're you're like let's all come to the
table so you've got a a a Symphony of
voices in there that are all you that
you know to be you right and you know
how to have those convers you're not
afraid to be in those conversations and
then you know which what the outcome of
that committee decision is and you put
it into real world action and the world
only sees the action that's it and only
you can know your internal dialogue and
only I can know my internal dialogue and
the only way to quote unquote know it is
to spend a hell of a lot of time there
that's right okay a life time got it a
lifetime like think about it for me to
be sitting here in front of you you're
not going to call 300 PB Eco laab guy to
come sit here you might I don't know
maybe probably not probably not think
about
this what we teach people is kind
kindness to
yourself do you think if I taught myself
kindness and I agree with it God people
so many people take me out of context
it's
ridiculous take it however the you
want to take it when I was 300
lb where you think that conversation
would have got me if I spoke kindness to
myself I tell you where it gets me right
back to 7-Eleven another box of mini
chocolate donuts and the chocolate
milkshake that's the one
voice that's the one voice that most of
us have that you're talking about if you
don't have a conversation in there the
other voice that you create that says
okay how does this look looks very
ugly that kind conversation for me went
away a long time ago which is why the
dialogue is now which you see a lot of
action because most people have inaction
because there's one person talking and
that one person's always lean you down
the same path the path that makes you
feel very comfortable and happy with
yourself
the second you create the other voice
there's
conflict there's battles there's
Wars there's defeat one thing I learned
I taught myself this and people go I
don't understand what you're saying I'm
G try to break it down real
quick I didn't teach myself Victory
first I taught myself
failure I taught myself how to
fail and people that's so depressing is
it when you're 300 pounds and you can't
read and write and you're up how
many times you're going to fail
on that process so if you don't know how
to fail there is no
Victory I never talked about winning
because I knew the path to winning was
it be years of failing first so I taught
myself how to fail
properly no one teaches you how to
fail but if you're going out for
insurmountable odds that make
absolutely no sense a black kid
that can't swim 300 pound will be a Navy
SEAL
okay you better teach yourself how to
fail first because if you sit in failure
for too long you will never come out of
it so the first part of My
Success was learning how to fail
properly and then eventually
I started getting a few
victories but that's what people don't
get when you have buried yourself in
such a deep hole you better
first talk about the failures you're
going to have first and that's when that
other voice comes up it tells you we got
to do something but it also tells you
boy I'm not gonna lie to you Goggins
you're in for a climb bro you're
gonna get your ass handed to you made
fun of the outside noise the inside
noise both voices are going to be
telling you to go yourself
you are in for hell
bro I am so brother leers fail so this
is what you mean when you say that
whatever anyone says it's insignificant
insignificant as right it's the cap
gun fire because it's just like it
because the voice in your own head is is
far worse and I should say sorry one of
the voices in your head yes yeah I'm
being very like detailed almost surgical
about that because I think this thing
about inner dialogue we think is one
voice yes you're making it clear it's
many voices it is and the thing about it
is you you you have to be really and
sometimes all the voices are telling you
the wrong man but through Years
Years not a podcast or listening to a
book or reading a book years of
sacrifice of suffering of diligent
pinpoint work on what you want
to do for yourself not like oh let me
just do a bunch of let me I want to
be in every task possible no pinpoint
what I want to do with my life what
happens is you have all these voices
that are telling you you're up
and this is could to be hard but for
some reason you put so much practice
into
you that you can ignore every one of
them that are telling you you're not
going to make it
and still be able to make
it because you have put the practice in
that you know this is the process it's
such a daunting task that all the voices
are saying no but you still have the
conviction that I know I can do this and
that's what it took for me to get
here 20 30 years ago I had this 35 or
whatever it was 3 to 25 years ago pipe
dream
and ever since then every voice was like
you're a
nut but when you put that practice and
every day you lace them up and I don't
mean run it's just a metaphor for life
when you lace them up
every day pretty soon you win pretty
soon you'll win you have the
courage and the heart and the dedication
and the mindset about everybody can go
themselves I know what I know I've
listened to myself enough to
know I know what I know none of you can
hear what I'm
hearing and that's what people don't do
enough of they don't listen to their
Journey they listen to everybody else is
before you know it I'm crazy but if
I'm so crazy why am I so
successful how that
happen I'm
so misguided and Mis and up and
don't listen to
him why am I the only one to do a whole
bunch of why am I troll
Blazer why how is that possible how can
you be up and also self-made the
same no no
obviously you're not looking at the
truth in front of you the truth in front
of you is it sucks it's
painful it's mind
numbing and that is the truth and that's
why a lot of people don't like listening
to me because this is what it takes
creating another voice and sometimes
going at it alone all the time going at
it alone because no one's going to
believe in you and that's
that what I'm about to say is not
conjecture and I can say that with
confidence because I did a four episode
guest series with a a brilliant
psychiatrist a guy named Paul KY from
Trenton he's a Stanford Harvard trained
guy he's also got a lot of Street in him
he's had his own hardship real
hardship he's brilliant and he said
something that I'll never forget which
is you know we think that the the
forbrain the part of our brain that
creates strategy Etc is the
supercomputer he said no no no no no no
it's like the supercomputer of the brain
is the is the unconscious mind it's the
part of our mind that's controlling most
everything and most people unfortunately
don't do the work to understand how
their unconscious is controlling them
and that's this scary thing this idea
like your mind is controlling you you
know and I'm not going to get into the
Free Will debate I believe in at least
some
will I believe what you're describing
and this internal
dialogue I think you have access to your
unconscious mind you by listening to the
dialogue going inward we know this is
true in sleep in dreams in meditation
and just by shutting out everything else
shutting out all the external noise
which is filled with things that pull us
to noise makes it sound bad but it's
it's the gravitational pull of all the
things that just allow us to distract
ourselves without knowing
that you know the ice cream the have a
cookie the merry
Christmas the unconscious mind this huge
piece of the iceberg underneath that
Paul calls the the supercomputer he's
saying that with knowledge as a
neurobiologist psychiatrist psychologist
he really knows that's the piece that if
one does real introspection he calls it
the cupboards you got to look in the
cupboards and it's often really scary
what you find in there and most people
are just like I don't even want to know
the cupboards are there but you're
pulling all the cupboard doors is
open and then you're and I'm you're
extremely deliberate with what gets put
into
action you're not just going oh like I'm
pissed so I'm gonna act pissed or I'm
you know tired so I'm gonna act tired
it's you're picking very carefully what
to
do and that's a process that I'm
guessing came to you does it come to you
as a okay it makes sense why running
makes sense it makes sense why smoke
jumping makes sense
so it seems like a
huge portion of your time is
spent understanding yourself and making
sense to you and so when people don't
understand you it's got to be extra
frustrating yes because most people
don't understand themselves so that
we're all running around going like
you're this and you're that because most
people are just unwilling to look Inward
and I'm including myself by the way I
mean I've done a fair amount of
introspection but I'm inspired today
that word inspired but it's true
motivated to start going inward further
cuz it is scary it's like we don't know
what's in those cupboards and it's
terrifying yes especially because we
don't know and those are the first ones
that open up and like he talked about
you got to go through those cups I do
spring clean every day in those
dark cupboards those th those dark
cabinets the ones I start with first
that's the real me
man that's the real me that's why I'm
not
ashamed I don't hide I used to hide I
don't hide anymore he's exactly right I
I don't know all the science
behind I know what I know that's
why I don't listen to anybody anymore I
don't listen to I think most people
are full of because I know I know
the deep dark secrets of those
cupboards it's ugly man and every day
I'm talking to him every day I'm
cleaning them I'm cleaning them and I'm
talking to the same demons that came out
of those cups as I'm as I'm
cleaning them sometimes they go right
back in them
again it's not easy and this is why most
most of us just Why am
misunderstood because what comes out of
those cabinets that I'm
cleaning sometimes they see on
Instagram sometimes they'll see in the
podcast sometimes they see in this one I
turn people off open up your own
cabinets and then go talk about it let
me see how pretty it looks let me see
how pretty you sound let me see how put
together your words are I bet you a
or a comes out because for
you to go back in there again to clean
the same cabin that the demon
came out of take some big balls bro to
do it every day of your life to go back
in there and spring clean every day not
once a year once every decade
every day you know it gets dusty and
every day you don't start with the with
the victories you don't go oh this is
nice look at my look at my I love me
while let me clean up this little Dusty
no I go right for the things that are
GNA keep me buried I go right there
first because if I don't clean those out
first the day doesn't
start so what he's saying to me is
truth and like I told you many times
today I could never figure out how to
explain this to people because I'm
not neuron nothing I'm just a guy that
said okay we got to start in the dungeon
and we got to stay here for the rest of
our lives for you to become successful
the dungeon is a place that has to be
clean and it's the scariest place to be
that's why I'm misunderstood because I'm
speaking from the dungeon that's why I
am
successful because I go there every damn
day and that is the truth what he says
it's the exact truth those cabinets are
Dusty dirty and scary as
broken
glass
dark spiders
cobwebs but most of all your biggest
fears the biggest things that put you in
the up place you are today are in
there that's why we all like to keep
them shut even like to lock them up act
like they never happen that's why you
never grow you never improve you never
have real conversations like we're
having right now never never oh no no no
no no no let's not no no no let's not go
there I talk to so many people who tell
me
that let's talk about this cuz they'll
tell me but they can only say it once
and they'll say it in passing they won't
get deep in the weeds with it like you
can't just clean it you
gotta spitshine that you
got to relive it every detail of
it you can't like oh yeah yeah my dad
beat me and you know you know it is what
it is hey is what it is
it's it's killing you it's taking over
your whole life but that's the
convers yeah my dad I'm fine now though
I'm good okay all right no you ain't you
ain't fine you ain't fine this is this
is real talk people don't to have that
so your boy's right 100% right scary as
it's scary as but makes you
who you're supposed to be
and that's the test we forget we we
think we're supposed to breathe air and
have kids and pay the bills and
every what what's this life about
that make no
sense being tested my friend tests
come when you have not
studied tests come when you think that
you're in the great place that's that's
the test the test is every day of your
life and most of us fail because because
we don't know why we're here because we
don't go inward to say oh you gave me a
lot of to fix man and this test
sucks but then you
start David
goggin I don't think I could add to that
I know I
can't thank you for sharing what you
shared
today I
mean as much as
your process or anyone's process can't
be completely understood from the
outside you gave us a real window into
this thing this process that you was as
you said God put it on you I believe in
God too people can believe what they
want but I somehow your your life God
gave you these challenges early on and
then there was a point where you went
internal mhm
and like you said you developed a skill
but it's a perishable skill yep and you
clearly live in the process of opening
those cupboards reopening those
coverboards trying to spit shine those
cupboards understanding that they're
never ever really done but that you can
gain ground on them that you can win day
after day after day and you really
shared a lot of concrete things that I
think I know know people are going to be
able to apply if they choose right and I
agree with you I think most people will
be like whoa that was a lot yep it's
heavy I think I want to just kind of
bake myself in Netflix
and check mix yep
instead but there's
also the reality that there are men and
women boys and girls who hear that and
go okay and start cracking the the
cupboards open right and I I just know
that you know for myself I'm extremely
grateful that you're willing to put it
all out there you're so brutally honest
so brutally authentic that word
authenticity gets thrown around so
much and I can tell you that for me and
for everybody else like that's what
really what resonates so whether or not
you want to whether or not it's the
purpose behind it or not you're lighting
the path so thank you respect thank you
thanks for having me thank you for
joining me for today's discussion with
David Goggins to learn more about David
and to find links to his two fantastic
books can't hurt me and never finished
please see the show note captions if
you're learning from and or enjoying
this podcast please subscribe to our
YouTube channel that's a terrific zero
cost way to support us in addition
please subscribe to the podcast on both
Spotify and apple and on both Spotify
and apple you can leave us up to a
five-star review please also check out
the sponsors mentioned at the beginning
and throughout today's episode that's
the best way to support this podcast if
you have questions or comments about the
hubman Lab podcast or if you have
suggestions about guests or topics that
you'd like me to cover please put those
in the comment section on YouTube I do
read all the comments not on today's
episode but on many previous episodes of
The hubman Lab podcast we discuss
supplements while supplements aren't
necessary for everybody many people
derive tremendous benefit from them for
things like improving sleep for hormone
support and for Focus if you'd like to
learn more about the supplements
discussed on the huberman Lab podcast
please go to Liv momentus spelled o us
so that's Liv mous.com
huberman if you're not already following
me on social media I am huberman lab on
all social media platforms so that's
Instagram Twitter threads X LinkedIn and
Facebook and on all those platforms I
discuss science and science related
tools some of which overlaps with the
content of the hubman Lab podcast but
much of which is distinct from the
content on the hubman Lab podcast so
again it's hubman lab on all social
media platforms if you haven't already
subscribed to our neural network
newsletter I encourage you to do so it
is completely zero cost and it provides
podcast summaries and protocols in the
form of brief PDFs of one to three pages
things like deliberate cold exposure a
protocol for foundational Fitness a
protocol for deliberate heat exposure
for managing dopamine for optimizing
your sleep and so on and so on again
completely zero cost you simply go to
hubman lab.com go to the menu scroll
down to newsletter and click on the
newsletter Tab and you enter your email
to sign up but I should point out that
we do not share your email with anybody
thank you once again for joining me for
today's discussion with the one and only
David gogins and last but certainly not
least thank you for your interest in
science
[Music]